<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo learned sermons The one, of the mischieuous subtiltie, and barbarous crueltie, the other of the false doctrines, and refined hæresis of the romish synagogue. / Preached, the one at Paules Crosse the 5. of Nouember, 1608. The other at the Spittle the 17. of Aprill. 1609. In the first, are examined diuers passages of that lewde English libell, written by a prophane fugitiue, against the Apologie for the Oath of Allegeance. In the seconde, are answered many of the arguments published by Rob. Chambers priest, concerning popish miracles; and dedicated (forsooth) to the Kings most excellent Maiestie. By Robert Tynley, Doctor of Diuinitie, and Archdeacon of Ely.</title>
            <author>Tynley, Robert, 1561 or 2-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118816</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854023</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1041:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo learned sermons The one, of the mischieuous subtiltie, and barbarous crueltie, the other of the false doctrines, and refined hæresis of the romish synagogue. / Preached, the one at Paules Crosse the 5. of Nouember, 1608. The other at the Spittle the 17. of Aprill. 1609. In the first, are examined diuers passages of that lewde English libell, written by a prophane fugitiue, against the Apologie for the Oath of Allegeance. In the seconde, are answered many of the arguments published by Rob. Chambers priest, concerning popish miracles; and dedicated (forsooth) to the Kings most excellent Maiestie. By Robert Tynley, Doctor of Diuinitie, and Archdeacon of Ely.</title>
                  <author>Tynley, Robert, 1561 or 2-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Hall for Thomas Adams,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "Histoire des miracles advenus a l'intercession de la glorieuse vierge Marie, au lieu dict Montaigu" by Philippe Numan and "The judgment of a Catholicke English-man, living in banishment for his religion" by Robert Parsons.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Numan, Philippe, d. 1617. --  Histoire des miracles advenus a l'intercession de la glorieuse vierge Marie, au lieu dict Montaigu --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Parsons, Robert, 1546-1610. --  Judgment of a Catholicke English-man, living in banishment for his religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625. --  Triplici nodo, triplex cuneus --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Chambers, Robert, 1571-1624?</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO LEARNED SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONS.</p>
            <p>The one, of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous ſubtiltie, and barbarous cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, the other of the falſe Doctrines, and <hi>refined Haereſis of the Romiſh Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preached, the one at Paules Croſſe the</hi> 5. <hi>of Nouember,</hi> 1608. <hi>The other at the Spittle the</hi> 17. <hi>of Aprill.</hi> 1609.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the first, are examined diuers paſſages of that lewde</hi> Engliſh Libell, written by a Prophane Fugitiue, againſt the Apologie for the Oath of Allegeance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the ſeconde, are anſwered many of the arguments pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhed</hi> by <hi>Rob. Chambers</hi> Prieſt, concerning Popiſh Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; and Dedicated (forſooth) to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Tynley,</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Ely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Hall</hi> for <hi>Thomas Adams.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER, <hi>GRACE AND PEACE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am to pray thee (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader) not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it to the itching humour of theſe times, (wherein the ſaying of the Poet is truly verifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Scribimus indocti, docti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp;c.</hi> neuer more writing and printing, from the pens of the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as well as the learned;) nor to any vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory that J ſeeke in publiſhing theſe Sermons, which I made account ſhould haue had their last period with the compaſſe of the times wherein they were deliuered. Jt is the authoritie of ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h as
<pb facs="tcp:19429:3"/> with mee is ſacred, and whoſe word is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that they come further abroad, to thy view, then I intended when I made my firſt rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning.</p>
            <p>Wherein if thou ſhalt finde ought that may ſerue for thy inſtruction, and better ſtrengthning in theſe laſt and perilous times, wherein there are ſo many back-ſliders, and fallers away from the truth; I ſhall thinke my labour, whatſoeuer, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly rewarded, and God ſhall haue the praiſe and glory of it.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe was, in the firſt of them, to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thine eies the wilie ſnares, and cruelty of the <hi>Romiſh Synagogue,</hi> by whoſe firie zeale and blinde deuotion, the powder-treaſon was neere vpon the kindling: from which most barbarous and bloody treacherie being deliuered, beyond all that man could imagine and conceiue, by his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence and powerfull hand, which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all in all, (when we were like ſheepe appointed to the ſlaughter, and as ſilly birds, ready to be intrapped by the ſnares of the Fowlers) if wee ſhould bee ſilent in Gods praiſes, or forgetfull of that our wonderfull deliuerance, well may <hi>our right hands forget their cunning, and our
<pb facs="tcp:19429:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> tongues for euer cleaue to the roofes of our mouthes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jn the latter, I haue to my abilitie done my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to giue thee warning of the <hi>falſe Prophet;</hi> who was neuer more buſie then he is now, <hi>compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſea and land to make a Proſelyte,</hi> one of his profeſsion; <hi>and when he is ſo, making him two-fold more the childe of Hell then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felfe is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou maiſt thereout obſerue the ſhop and forge where popiſh doctrine is hammered, euen vpon the anuill of old haereſies, long ſithence condemned by the Catholike Church; howſoeuer the Ieſuites (the Pope his holy anker) garniſh and poliſh it with their rhetoricall flowers, and by all the paines and skill that is in them, to make it ſalable to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which cannot iudge of their colours.</p>
            <p>Read iudiciouſly, and with a minde that loueth truth; not praeoccupated with a praeiudicate opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and I hope thou ſhalt finde ſomething that may fauour with thy reliſh.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Momes,</hi> that are ready to carpe at all mens paines, when themſelues will not put to one finger to helpe ſupport the common burden; J paſſe not for them; the rather becauſe I hope to find
<pb facs="tcp:19429:4"/> them more indifferent Iudges, which know what belongeth to theſe labours. To whoſe learned and charitable cenſure I ſubmit my ſelfe, and commend thee to the bleſſed prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Almighty. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Charge of</hi> Wictham <hi>in</hi> Eſſex, <date>
                     <hi>23. Maij. Anno 1609.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>The leaſt of all thy Brethren, R. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader. It is the faſhion of ſome men that write or ſpeake, that they are ready and deſirous to haue the ſame put in Print. It fared other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with the Author of theſe two godly &amp; learned Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he hath beene intreated by diuers his good friends to publiſh them, yet hee could hardly bee brought therunto, vntil ſuch time as hee was perſwaded, that as they did edifie, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent many hundreds that heard them preached, ſo would they, being printed, inſtruct, and ſtrengthen many that ſhould reade them, againſt the ſubtiltie, &amp; impietie of Poperie, which ſecretly is buzzed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heads of the ſimpler ſort. Vpon which reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſo they might bee beneficiall vnto God his church, he hath at the laſt condiſcended to the putting of them in print. And I doubt not but as to his credit, ſo to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of all that ſhal read them. And ſo I leaue thee to God his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and holy protection.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Faults to be amended in the two firſt ſheetes printed before it was throughly corrected.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>FOr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> page</hi> 2. <hi>in the Margent. read</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> Fremel <hi>ibid, read</hi> Tremel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> in aeſtu <hi>page.</hi> 5. <hi>line</hi> 13. <hi>read</hi> ni aſtu.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> may names <hi>pag.</hi> 6. <hi>line</hi> 5. <hi>read</hi> many names.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> quilibit <hi>ibid line</hi> 11. <hi>read</hi> quilibet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> he recuſant <hi>page.</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 17. <hi>read</hi> the recuſant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> falſe <hi>page</hi> 11. <hi>line</hi> 26. <hi>reade</hi> falſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> common-wealth <hi>page</hi> 12. <hi>line</hi> 31. <hi>read</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> is kindled, <hi>page</hi> 15. <hi>line</hi> 3. <hi>read</hi> was kindled.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SONG OF DEGREES. <hi>A PSALME OF DAVIDS.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME 124.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERS. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl> If the Lord had not beene on our ſide (may Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael now ſay.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </bibl> If the Lord had not beene on our ſide, when men roſe vp againſt vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>3.</hi>
                     </bibl> They had then ſwallowed vs vp quicke, when their wrath was kindled againſt vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </bibl> Then the waters had drowned vs, and the ſtreame had gone ouer our ſoules.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>5.</hi>
                     </bibl> Then had the ſwelling waters gone ouer our ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>6.</hi>
                     </bibl> Praiſed be the Lord, which hath not giuen vs as a pray vnto their teeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7.</hi>
                     </bibl> Our ſoule is eſcaped, euen as a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowlers: the ſnare is broken, and we are deliuered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>8.</hi>
                     </bibl> Our helpe is in the name of the Lord, which hath made heauen and earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O enter into a diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the title of this <hi>Pſalme</hi> [<hi>A Song of Degrees</hi>] common to the foure <hi>Pſalmes</hi> immediately going before this, and to the ten enſuing after; were (as I ſuppoſe) more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to obſerue the varietie of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions old and new, then to come to a knowledge of the truth therein.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19429:6"/>
            <p>The <hi>Iewiſh Rabbins</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Caluin. &amp; Jacob. de Valent.</note> (whoſe manner is, when matters are obſcure, like <hi>Painters</hi> and <hi>Poets,</hi> to come and faine any thing) obſerue, that there were fifteene ſteps or degrees, in a part of the Temple, appointed for men; when women had their place below: to which fifteene ſteps, theſe fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene <hi>Pſalmes</hi> of degrees had a reference.<note n="b" place="margin">Luther.</note> Others thinke they were ſo called, becauſe they were wont to be ſung by the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Leuites,</hi> vpon certaine ſteps and degrees in the Temple, as on a higher place, that they might be the better heard by the people. Of ſuch ſteps and degrees, there is mention made, in the like caſe, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9. <hi>verſe</hi> 4.<note n="c" place="margin">Baſil. Beza. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Some expound them hiſtorically, by way of Aſcenſions, (as the word ſignifieth) namely, of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> aſcending vp to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in returning from their capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie; to the memorie of which benefit, they were princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſecrated.<note n="d" place="margin">Baſil. Arnobius. Hierome. Auguſtine. Caſſiodorus.</note> Some myſtically, of Gods children, profiting in this world of their peregrination, riſing from ſinne to grace, and aſcending by degrees from vertue to vertue, vntill they appeare before God, in the heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> In which current, the ancient Fathers run, for the moſt part.<note n="e" place="margin">Caluin.</note> Some of an higher tune or note, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they roſe, in lifting vp their voices, when they ſung them.<note n="f" place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emel &amp; Junius.</note> Laſt of all, ſome in regard of the excellencie of that dittie, expounding the word, of excellencies. <hi>A ſong of excellencies,</hi> that is, an excellent ſong, like that <hi>Song of Songs,</hi> that excellent Song of <hi>Salomons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howſoeuer, I take it, the matter is not great, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy any curious enquirie after the name, ſo long as wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the ſubſtance and matter of the <hi>Pſalme:</hi> that it is indeed an excellent <hi>Pſalme,</hi> deſcribing in liuely colours the ſtate of Gods Church vpon the earth, ſo expoſed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, as that ſometime, like a generall deluge, they are ready to drowne it, verſ. 4.5. ſometimes like ſauage beaſts, to teare it in peeces, verſ. 6. yea not making any bones of it, to deuoure and ſwallow it vp quicke at once, verſ. 3. ſometimes like craftie fowlers, with ginnes and ſnares to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19429:6"/> entrap it. verſ. 7. So malitiouſly are they bent, ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſlie are they incenſed againſt it. verſ. 3. But that God, who by his power made heauen and earth, and by the ſame his power, ruleth it ſtill, as beſt pleaſeth him, verſ. 8. was euermore at hand, thereby vpholding it; and at one ſide thereof; and then no matter who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. verſ. 1.2. Maugre their wrath and malice, they could not preuaile, for they loſt their prey, verſ. 6. The godly eſcaped as a bird out of the ſnare, and were deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, verſ. 7. What remaineth then, but that the Lord be praiſed for this their deliuerance. verſ. 6. For he was their onely helpe then; and in his holy name they will ſet vp their reſt. verſ. 8.</p>
            <p>I haue, after my Country manner, briefly analized, and paraphraſtically, in few words, deliuered you the ſenſe and meaning of the Prophet in this <hi>Pſalme:</hi> which howſoeuer it ſpread it ſelfe like a moſt fruitfull tree, into many bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; my purpoſe is, omitting others, to make choice of theſe points, to inſiſt vpon: 1. The ſubtiltie of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the Church, in laying ſnares to entrap it, as fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers doe to catch birds, out of the 7. verſe. 2. Their crueltie, in ſeeking to teare it in peeces, yea to ſwallow it vp quicke, as ſome cruell beaſts doe their prey; or, as mighty inundations, ouerflow whatſoeuer commeth in their way, out of the 3.4.5. and 6. verſes. 3. The cauſe producing theſe effects of ſubtiltie and crueltie in theſe aduerſaries; namely, their wrath; out of the 3. verſe. 4. The deliuerance of the Church from her enemies, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their craft and crueltie, by the omnipotent power of almighty God; out of the 1.2.6. and 7. verſes. Laſt of all, the dutie performed for this deliuerance; praiſe and thanksgiuing to the Lord, verſe 6.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt therefore of the ſubtiltie of the enemies of the Church; wherein the holy Prophet likeneth them to fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, laying their ſnares ſo couertly, ſhadowed ouer with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing baits, that they draw and allure the ſilly bird, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19429:7"/> Church, vntill ſhe be brought within compaſſe of the net, and ſo become the fowlers prey.</p>
            <p>A wile as ancient as the world is old, and plotted by the father of wiles the Diuell, againſt the Church, when ſhee was in her infancie, in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> our firſt parents in Paradiſe: whoſe happineſſe in that ſtate of innocencie, and felicitie in a garden of all delightfull pleaſures, the enemie of mankinde ſubuerted, by a trap of more ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing happineſſe in ſhew; deliuering to the woman the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit,<note place="margin">Gen 3.5.</note> ſo canded with the entiſing hope of <hi>Eritis ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut dii,</hi> Ye ſhall be as Gods, that ſhe forgat Lord and Loare, God and his Commandements, taking and eating it, and giuing it to her husband; wrapping him in the ſame ſnare with her ſelfe; whereby, both of them, with all their ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding poſteritie, were made their enemies pray. Whil'ſt they would be as Gods, they ceaſe to be as men, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red now to the beaſts that periſh;<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.12.</note> not continuing in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wherein they were created; but inthralled to death, by tranſgreſſing the Commandement. Such now is the end of one and all of vs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nimrods</hi> and Fowlers of the world (to make good the old prouerbe,<note place="margin">Eſa. 24 2. Ezek. 16.44.</note> 
               <hi>Like Maſter, like Seruant;</hi> and, <hi>As the mother is ſo is the daughter)</hi> do heerein reſemble the nature of their father the diuell; transforming themſelues into all ſhapes, and laying their ginnes to catch the ſimple and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent. Witneſſe <hi>Ioab,</hi> who taking <hi>Abner</hi> aſide, vnder pretence to ſpeake with him peaceably, ſmote him vnder the fift rib, that he died, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.27. And incouraging himſelfe in this miſchiefe, not long after, hee greeted <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſa</hi> with the like ſalutation, enquiring after his welfare, <hi>Art thou in health, my brother?</hi> and taking him by the beard with his right hand to kiſſe him, but with the other, ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing his ſword in his bowels, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Iudas</hi> his <hi>Aue Rabbi,</hi> God ſaue thee, Maſter, was much like this treacherie; and his kiſſe, whereby he betraied his Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of them that ſought his blood, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.47.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19429:7"/> So cunningly and as commonly, are the ſugred names of friend and Brother, Lord and Maiſter, made ſnares for miſchiefe, <hi>Cum venena Latent circumlita melle verborum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de ſum. bono. ca. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> whilſt the poiſon (ſaith <hi>Iſidore</hi>) lyeth hid, ſpred ouer with the hunnie of ſweet words, the impoſter making a ſhew of vertue and honeſtie, vntil hee get within a man, and fetch him ouer.</p>
            <p>For this they learne by experience, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth in a treatiſe againſt the Gentiles; that hee which wil deceiue, muſt ſet a good face vpon it; and make the matter ſeeme, at leaſt wiſe probable; elſe were they not their crafts-maſter: for as the commicall Poet ſaith, <hi>doli,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> 
               <hi>doli non ſunt, in aeſtu colas,</hi> guiles are no guiles, if deceite cloake them not:<note place="margin">Chryſ. contra gentil.</note> and <hi>malum maximum ſi id palam proue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat;</hi> no greater miſchiefe then if they bee ſeene. For ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the pray is loſt, and they goe home emptie-handed; as fowlers doe, when the birds eſpie the net.</p>
            <p>But there lyeth the skill, to ſpread the net, that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare not; that the baite hide the hooke: wherin, how wel the aduerſaries of our Church haue profited, let the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites of our times teſtifie for all the reſt, whoſe verie name ſerueth for nothing elſe, (as by their practiſe is euident;) but as <hi>Hierom</hi> writeth in the like caſe, <hi>fraudem facere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Ruſticum.</note> to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuent vs. So farre are they from that Dooue-like ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie; to which, the Lord Ieſus (and from whome they would deriue their name,) exhorteth his Diſciples, Math. 10. verſe 16.</p>
            <p>There are that haue branded them with this marke.<note place="margin">Ieſuits Catac. li. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>156.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There is not in the world any beaſt more ſubtill then is the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite; not the Fox,</hi> which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 19, Sermon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth thus: <hi>Vulpis calliditate Potens, inuentrix doli, frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis artifex, ſimulationis magiſtra, ſimplicitatis vacua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mutato nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, de te fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la narratur.</note> 
               <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtrophis.</hi> Change the name &amp; you may render it thus: the Ieſuite is a beaſt, powerfull in craft, an inuentor of guile, the artizen of deceite; maiſter of fauning, deuoid of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, and full of wily ſubtiltie.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19429:8"/>
            <p>For whereunto tendeth it, that one Ieſuite muſt bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by ſo many names?<note place="margin">Proceedins a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt he late Traitors.</note> as <hi>Garnet</hi> that moſte treacherous Prouinciall <hi>Wallye,</hi> alias <hi>Darcie,</hi> alias <hi>Roberts,</hi> alias <hi>Farmer,</hi> alias <hi>Philips?</hi> Is it not, that going masked vnder ſo may names, as vnder ſo many viſards hee may the more ſecurely lay his ſnares to entrap vs? what is their drift in transforming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues into as many ſhapes as they meete with obiects? now a Courtiour, then a Cittizen; heere a countrie Gentleman; there a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie Swaine: ſometimes a Seruingma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; a ſwaggerer, Pot-companion; another while a Prieſt; in a word <hi>euerie man for euerie bodie, a quilibit for a quolibet, a Polipus for all orders and degrees?</hi> Is it not, that by this meanes, they may come within men of all ſorts; inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate themſelues into their companies; creepe into their boſoms; prie into their hearts; that ſo they may more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beguile them vnawares.</p>
            <p>But of all their Wiles, I commend vnto you, the Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocating <hi>Sibboleth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 1.2.6.</note> the verie forge of lying and deceit; which bewraieth them by their ſpeech, to bee no other then falſe faining <hi>Ephraemites.</hi> By this they affirme and deny, ſweare and forſweare, and all with a breath: they are Prieſts, and they are no Prieſts, that is to tell you, they ſay Maſſe, and they ſay not Maſſe, that is, in <hi>Pauls Quier</hi> or in <hi>Weſtminſter Quier.</hi> When they talke with our Magiſtrates, they ſpeake as to the Walles; for men with them are no men, and all by vertue of this mixt propoſition: their Gorgons head, (a point in Logicke which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> neuer taught, and the ancient ſchooles knew it not) wherby they goe beyond the courſe of nature, making things meerely contradictorie to ſubſiſt.</p>
            <p>Let mee trouble your patience with one inſtance, which ſhall bee worthy your obſeruation. When a Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſhall ſweare; for example, in taking the Oath of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, according to the expreſſe words of the Oath, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plaine and common ſenſe and vnderſtanding of the ſame words, without any Aequiuocation, or mentall euaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19429:8"/> or ſecret reſeruation whatſoeuer.</hi> Could it be imagined that any ſhifting or cauelling wit ſhould bee able to finde a ſtarting hole in the ſame, to winde himſelfe out of it? yet beholde an Engliſh Catholike (as hee nameth himſelfe) but indeede the verie fierie match of this ſtate and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) in a letter written to a friend of his; hath (as hee would beare others in hand) found a meanes to auoid the force of this Oath, by Aequiuocating: as namely where it is ſaid <hi>That the Pope hath no Authoritie to depoſe our King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. 18.19.</note> 
               <hi>nor to dispoſe of his Kingdomes,</hi> &amp; ſo forward what concerneth the Pope: true ſaith he, <hi>Without iuſt cauſe;</hi> or <hi>directly hee cannot; or in ſome ſuch like ſenſe.</hi> When as the deponent, ſweareth directly againſt all, and euerie ſuch mentall eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſecret reſeruation whatſoeuer; and that hartily, and wittingly, and truely; or elſe, let him refuſe the Oath, and not ſweare at all.</p>
            <p>Heere is the verie quinteſſence of this cogging Artt: he recuſant taketh the Oth according to the expreſſe words; not ſo ſaith our Engliſh Catholike, but hee muſt Aequiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: the Recuſant followeth the plaine and ordinarie ſenſe and meaning of the words; our Engliſh Catholike teacheth him to keepe ſomewhat in his minde, by ſecret reſeruation: the Recuſant abiureth and ſweareth againſt all mentall euaſion; our Engliſh Catholike inſtructeth him to make eſcape, by his mixt propoſition; expreſſing a part of his minde by word of mouth, and reſeruing an other part in his heart. Whether this bee to make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of Faith and a good conſcience, malitiouſly and of ſet purpoſe; by open and manifeſt periurie, let any man iudge, which doth not wilfully ſhut his eyes againſt the noone-light? and being paſt feeling, is by Gods iuſtice giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Ye ſee the foulers of our times; their nets, their ſleights, their wiles; wherein they goe beyond the Foxes in ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in hunting after their prey. What remaineth, but that wee humbly deſire our vigilant Magiſtrates, (to whome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19429:9"/> the charge of the Lords vineyard is committed) to take theſe Foxes both great and ſmall: for what doe they elſe, but ſpoile and deſtroy our vines, which God hath placed amongſt vs, in this fruitfull ſoile? And that wee our ſelues ſetting their ſnares before our eyes, carefully ſhunne and auoide them, which elſe will bring vs to perdition both of body and ſoule. And this of the ſubtiltie of the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of our Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond circumſtance and propertie, whereby the Prophet deſcribeth them, is their crueltie; in renting and tearing Chriſt his flocke, and ſwallowing them vp quicke, as cruell beaſts doe their prey.</p>
            <p>It is not a new face of the Church; or proper to thoſe daies and ſeaſons, onely, which our Sauiour ſetteth foorth to our view.<note place="margin">Stel. in Luc.</note> Mat. 10.16. <hi>Behold I ſend you as ſheepe in the middeſt of Wolues,</hi> For in that, our Sauiour ſpeaketh in a time, neither paſt nor yet future to come, but in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (I ſend you) he thereby giueth vs to vnderſtand, that the dangers which are immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his ſheepe, conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing amongſt wolues, are alwaies preſent with them; there beeing no ſeaſon wherin they are free from their rage and crueltie: whether wee call to mind the times paſt, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what now is or heereafter ſhall enſue. <hi>In hoc ſeculo, in his diebus malis,</hi> in this world of wickedneſſe (ſaith the Godly Father Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) in theſe euill daies,<note place="margin">De Ciuit. dei. li. <hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>18</hi>
               </note> wherin ſinne hath got the vpper hand; the Church, as a ſtranger and Pilgrime, holdeth on her courſe, ſuſtained by Gods holy ſpirit; not onely, euer ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles conuerſed heere vpon the earth; but euen from the time of <hi>Abell</hi> the righteous, whoſe blood, his cruell brother <hi>Caine</hi> ſpilt vpon the earth. So ancient is the crueltie of theſe Wolues and rauenous beaſts, preying vpon Chriſt his Flocke; and ſo continuing from time to time as their rage and rauenous appetite hath edged them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>By the furie of theſe Wolues, the holy Prophets were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19429:9"/> conſumed, from <hi>Abel</hi> vnto <hi>Zacharias;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 23.35.</note> yea our Sauiour himſelfe was made a pray vnto them; whoſe example ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to inſtruct his flocke, in all ages, what they were to expect, and truſt vnto. For <hi>the diſciple is not aboue his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, nor the ſeruant aboue his Lord, Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. And if they <hi>haue done theſe things to the greenetree, what ſhall be done vnto the drie? Luke</hi> 23. <hi>verſe</hi> 31. The Apoſtles of our Sauiour, the rammes and bell-weathers of the flocke, haue all, in a manner, verified the words of their maſter: and what the condition of the Saints was in the Primitiue Church, the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> reporteth vnto vs: <hi>Some were racked, ſome tried with mockings, bonds, ſcourgings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. 11. v. 35. &amp;c</note> 
               <hi>impriſonment; ſome ſtoned, ſome hewen aſunder ſome ſlaine with the ſword.</hi> With which exquiſite torments, and many moe of like ſort, the crueltie of theſe Wolues could not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; but as <hi>Tacitus</hi> in his <hi>Annales</hi> recordeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Li.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Pereunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus addita ludibria,</hi> The Saints of God ſuffering martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome after this cruell manner, were further made laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtockes to the world; in being clad with skinnes of wilde beaſts, and ſo expoſed to the tearing and renting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder by dogges. And this not in ſome few, to the terror of the reſt, but as the ſame Author addeth, when the day was not long enough to make them away in, they ſerued <hi>in vſum nocturni luminis,</hi> for men to ſee by in the night, by the flames, wherein their bodies were conſumed. <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> goeth yet further, that the numbers in ſome places grew to be ſo great, that the executioners fainted with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, in their making hauocke, though one ſucceeded after another; and that the edges of their ſwords and ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, were dulled and made blunt with the multitude of the ſlaine bodies of the Saints; which he taketh not vp by way of credit, vpon other mens report; himſelfe was an eie witneſſe of it, in <hi>Thebais</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. hiſtor. lib. <hi>8.</hi> ca. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> So cruell was the rage of theſe rauenous beaſts, in theſe ten perſecutions, vnder the Romane Emperors.</p>
            <p>From which, if we ſuppoſe that the ages following were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19429:10"/> free,<note place="margin">Iob 40.10.</note> we erre and are greatly deceiued. <hi>Dilatat Behemoth caudam ſuam in fine mundi nequius. Behemoth</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie)</hi> enlargeth his taile (wherein lieth his ſtrength) more wickedly now in the end of the world;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moral.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 12</note> The Diuels wrath waxing greater in theſe Wolues his inſtruments, by how much ſhorter he knoweth his time is to wreake his malice vpon the Saints. So that, as <hi>Berna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> diſtinguiſheth, <hi>ſerm.</hi> 33. <hi>in Cantica, Pax eſt, &amp; non eſt pax;</hi> there is peace, and there is no peace. <hi>Pax a Paganis. &amp;c.</hi> The Church being in peace and reſt from <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels, ſed non profectò à filiis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 7.6.</note> but in ſooth not ſecured of her owne children, nor of them of her owne houſe, yea moſt infeſted by them: For who are they, that for theſe many yeeres haue made hauocke and ſpoile of the Church, but ſuch as would be tearmed,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> I ſay, not only <hi>Pillars,</hi> as were <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Iohn;</hi> but the very heads of the Church, Chriſt his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars vpon earth (as they ſtile themſelues) the <hi>Popes of Rome,</hi> that very <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſcarlet coloured Whore, drunké with the blood of Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Ieſus,<note place="margin">C. 17. v. 6.</note> as the Spirit teſtifieth in the <hi>Reuelations.</hi> Witneſſe, amongſt many others, the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Innocent</hi> the third ſo proceeded by his cenſures, that in one Towne of theirs, 17. thouſand of them were put to the ſword, without any reſpect had, of age, ſex, or degree: and in another Towne, one hundred and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore conſumed together in one fire, becauſe they would not abiure the faith of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſtor. part.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> 19. <hi>c.</hi> 1. §. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>Li.</hi> 4. <hi>pa.</hi> 1132.</note> as <hi>Antoninus</hi> reporteth: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> againſt whom, <hi>Paul</hi> the third excited <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperor, <hi>inſtigante Paulo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Genebrard</hi> their <hi>Chronologer;</hi> who, for the better managing of that warre, aſſiſted the Emperor with an Army out of <hi>Italie,</hi> of ten thouſand foot, and fiue hundred horſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the conduct of his Nephew <hi>Octauius Farneſius,</hi> who was ſo confident in his forces, that departing out of <hi>Italy,</hi> he boaſted before hand, that he would make ſuch a ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in <hi>Germanie,</hi> that his horſe ſhould ſwimme in the blood
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19429:10"/> of the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> as <hi>Iohn Sleidan</hi> is Author. Laſt of all,<note place="margin">Commentar. li. <hi>17.</hi> pa. <hi>534.</hi>
               </note> not to ſtand vpon examples, which in this kinde are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; witneſſe the ſlaughters and butcheries <hi>Factionis Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniticae,</hi> of the <hi>Hugonites</hi> in <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. li. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Natalis</hi> wronglie tearmeth them; of whom, to the number of ſixtie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, periſhed at <hi>Paris,</hi> and in other Cities of <hi>France,</hi> what time the <hi>Admirall</hi> was murdered: and in the ciuill warres, not ſo few as twelue hundred thouſand, naturall <hi>French,</hi> are numbred to haue beene ſlaine: in which combuſtions, the <hi>Popes of Rome</hi> were the very <hi>Alaſtores</hi> and <hi>Apollyons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brutum ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. p. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> the fire-brands of theſe miſchiefes.</p>
            <p>With whoſe flames, if this our natiue Countrie haue not in like manner burnt within theſe late yeeres, it was Gods watchfull eie ouer our Princes and vs, which extinguiſhed the ſparkes whil'ſt they were enkindling; and not want of malitious crueltie in them, who were alwaies ready preſt to miniſter fewell to theſe flames. The Buls of <hi>Pius</hi> 5. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 13. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. teſtifie as much, breathing out fire and ſword againſt our late Souereigne (whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie ſhall be bleſſed in all poſteritie) and by their loud lowing, calling in forraine powers againſt our Land, and exciting diſloyall ſubiects; as were <hi>Tichborne, Parry, Squier, Walpoole,</hi> and ſuch like, to treacherous conſpiracies at home: ſome of which conſpiracies, howſoeuer our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Catholike</hi> (hauing made his forehead as the <hi>Adamant</hi>) in his letter before mentioned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 34. <hi>&amp;</hi> 89.</note> tearme <hi>Ridiculous falfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, and monſtrous fictions, made againſt ſome Prieſts, to make their whole companie and cauſe odious:</hi> yet our Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, and benches of Iuſtice and Iudgement, haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced euidently this ſhameleſſe vntruth; and the Secular Prieſts haue likewiſe publiſhed as much,<note place="margin">Import. Con ſid. p. 16. &amp; p. 23, 33, 40.</note> concerning theſe treacheries, to all mens view. So that now it neceſſarily enſueth, <hi>ex ore proprio,</hi> from the confeſſion of our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, that the companie of theſe <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and their whole cauſe, is iuſtly odious both to God and man, for their treacherous and bloody deſignements.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19429:11"/>
            <p>From which aſperſions, in like manner, the two <hi>Breues</hi> of <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. will not be purged, although this <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> waſh them with niter (to vſe the words of the Prophet) and take much ſope to him.<note place="margin">Ier. 2.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>For moſt euident it is, that <hi>Catesby</hi> that Arch-Traitor, laid vpon them the foundations of the Powder-treaſon, in his conference with <hi>Garnet;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proceedings, R. 4.</note> arguing from their authority rightly and ſtrongly, that <hi>if it were lawfull not to receiue his Maieſtie, that now is, or to repell him, as the ſaid Breues did import; then it was alſo lawfull to expell or caſt him out.</hi> Which was endeuoured with no leſſe labour, then it was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by hope to bee effected by powder, from the vault: by which moſt barbarous ſtratagemme, like raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous beaſts, they would haue ſwallowed vs vp quicke, and ouer-whelmed vs with a flood, but not of water: thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps of powder, and ſtreames of fire, ſhould haue beene the ſwelling waters, which ſhould haue gone ouer our ſoules.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueton. in vita</note>
               <hi>C. Caligula,</hi> that monſter of mankinde, for his cruelty more then ſauage, is famous for a wiſh, that in his blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſtineſſe he conceiued againſt his ſubiects the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was, that they all had but one head, that ſo at one blow he might chop it off. But in this powder-treaſon, conſider cruelty more brutiſh then was euer that of <hi>Caligula:</hi> For heere not the Prince (with whom, vnder God, is ſtored vp all power of life and death) is plotting againſt the ſubiect, but the ſubiects againſt the Prince: and that not in heart only wiſhing, but by their practiſes labouring, yea in a manner effecting, not the ruine of a famous Citie, but of a flouriſhing Kingdome; and not of the Kingdome, the Common-wealth alone; but of the Church alſo: in both Church and Common-wealth, ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, not at the members without the head, but iointlie at both together, members and head alſo: not with the ſtroke of a ſword directed by mans hand, in whom ſtill reſideth mercie, but by the mercileſſe element of fire: and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19429:11"/> that not ordinarie, conſuming by degrees, but the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie inuention of the diuell, miniſtring that kinde of fewell to mans rage, which ſwalloweth vp at one breath, and as it were at one mouth-full, whatſoeuer ſtandeth in the way.</p>
            <p>The holy oile, wherewith his ſacred Maieſtie was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thronized into this royall Kingdome, ſhould haue beene no protection to defend him from the rage of this fire; though the <hi>Prophet,</hi> in Gods perſon, had before expreſly charged, <hi>Touch not mine anointed;</hi> the Law prouided,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.15. Deut. 22.6.</note> that men ſhould not take the damme with the yoong. Doth God take care of birds,<note place="margin">Cor.</note> as the Apoſtle reaſoneth in the like argument? or was it written for our ſakes? And yet in this ſhare, the mother muſt haue periſhed with the ſonne; root and branch together had beene conſumed in this combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. Gods iuſtice would haue ſpared <hi>Sodome,</hi> had there beene found in it but ten righteous:<note place="margin">Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.32.</note> but rauenous furie had ſo poſſeſſed theſe beaſts, that whom themſelues dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med iuſt, muſt haue periſhed with the reſt. The height of Maieſtie adorned with ſo many peereleſſe vertues, of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, wiſdome, godlineſſe, temperance, iuſtice, clemency; the matchleſſe Vine, with her tender plant, the future hope of our ſucceeding age; the noble Peeres, the moſt reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops, the wiſe Counſellors, the graue Sages of the Land, the Knights and Burgiſes, and Officers of all ſorts; all together, at one inſtant,<note place="margin">Lutheranum inuentum ad ignem rapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, vt ſic anima e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius in curru ignco, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Jeſaita Hoffaeus, ad inſeros feratur. Haſſemmil hiſtor. Ieſuitic. ca. <hi>6.</hi> pa. <hi>224.</hi> P. <hi>6. 7. 41.</hi> &amp;c. Pa. <hi>26. 42.</hi> &amp; <hi>125.</hi>
               </note> muſt haue mounted vp into this firie Chariot (as <hi>Hoffaeus</hi> that bloody <hi>Ieſuite</hi> was wont to ſay) that ſo their ſoules might haue beene harrowed into hell, if theſe Gunpowder-powder-inginers had been their Iudges.</p>
            <p>In this treacherieſo cruell and barbarous, as <hi>Impudency</hi> it ſelfe would be aſhamed, I ſay not, to excuſe, but, once to extenuate the hainouſneſſe of the attempt; ſee how our <hi>Engliſh Catholike</hi> plaieth the part of a diligent Aduocate, alleging the tribulation of <hi>Catholikes</hi> in our ſtate and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, meerely for conſcience and Religion (of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19429:12"/> which he greeuouſly complaineth in ſundry parts of his Letter) for the cauſe of this wofull attempt (to vſe his owne words) <hi>in theſe vnfortunate gentlemen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein, to paſſe ouer the ingratitude of this vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy perſon towards his gratious Maieſtie (of whoſe cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, not only the <hi>Recuſants</hi> in generall, but many of the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> haue been, and ſtill are partakers in great meaſure) I ſay only this, and that in a word, and I ſpeake it in the ſight and hearing of Almighty God, that if to bee a Rebell and a Traitor, be all one with a <hi>Catholike;</hi> and if due execution of iuſtice, be preſſure and tribulation; then I willingly acknowledge, that ſome <hi>Catholikes</hi> in <hi>England</hi> haue periſhed vnder this preſſure and tribulation. As for others, which ſuffer pecuniarie mulct in goods, or bodily reſtraint, or loſſe of Countrie by baniſhment; let him bee pleaſed to call to minde the fires and gibbets in <hi>Queene Maries</hi> daies, by which more innocents periſhed in ſome one or two yeeres, onely for profeſſion of the Goſpell, without the leaſt imputation of treaſon, then Popiſh Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of all ſorts, ſuffered in 45. yeeres of our late Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne, and in the ſix enſuing of his Maieſtie that now is; when as our holy Martyrs would haue reckoned it for great fauour, to haue gone away with life and limme, whatſoeuer became of their goods and natiue Country.</p>
            <p>Away then, euen for ſhame, with theſe foule blots and ſtaines of crueltie and perſecution: the milde and gentle aſpect of our mercifull King admitteth them not; neither are they found in our State: they are the vnſeparable markes and badges of the Romiſh Synagogue, as you haue heard; and of theſe holy Fathers, who rather ſucceed <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> in murders and ſlaughters,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The ſaying of</hi> Pope Adrian, Illine Catalog. teſtium verit. tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>483.</hi>
               </note> then <hi>S. Peter</hi> in feeding Chriſt his flocke. And this be ſpoken of the cruelty of the Aduerſaries of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3 I come now in the third place, to diſcuſſe the cauſe which produceth theſe effects of ſubtiltie and crueltie in the aduerſaries of the Church: wherby they ſeeke and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19429:12"/> indeuour the ſubuerſion and ruine thereof.</p>
            <p>The Prophet layeth it downe in the third verſe. <hi>They had ſwallowed vs vp quick when their wrath is kindled againſt vs.</hi> Wrath then was it that quickned the wits, and ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the rauening appetites of theſe enemies; making the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo wily in theirſnares; ſo powerfull in their forces; and all to the perdition of the ſilly and weake Lambes of Chriſt his flocke? An affection by nature incident in a man, but as <hi>Bernard</hi> well noteth, Sermon. 13. vpon the 91. Pſalme. <hi>abutentibus bono naturae, grauis perditio eſt, &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeranda pernicies:</hi> men abuſing natures good, it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a miſerable ruine, and heauie perdition; not to men onely, but to things alſo without reaſon, yea without ſenſe too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſpice nobiliſſimarum ciuitatum fundamenta vix notabilia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de ira. Cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> Behold ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi> the foundations of moſt noble Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, hardly to bee diſcerned, ſuch is their deſolation, <hi>has i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra deiecit,</hi> it was wrath that caſt them downe, and made them leuell with the ground. Conſider countries and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions made deſolate places, for many miles together; <hi>has ira exhauſit,</hi> it was wrath, that in this manner drew them drie, and made them void without an inhabitant. It was wrath that put the inſtruments of crueltie into the hands of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> thoſe Brethren in euill,<note place="margin">Gen, 49, 5</note> whereby they put <hi>Hamar</hi> and <hi>Shechem</hi> with their people to the ſword; and ſacked their Citie after they had receiued circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, breaking thereby the bonds of promiſe, and the very ſeale of their faith. And therefore moſt true is that verdit which the wiſe King hath giuen of this vnbridled affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Prouerb. 27.4. <hi>Anger is cruell, &amp; wrath is raging.</hi> And Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 29. Hom. to the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> as if he had foreſeene the powder-Treaſon, <hi>ira ignis vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens omnia deuorans,</hi> anger is like a mightie fire co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming all things. And Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> Ser. 1. <hi>De tempore, Iracun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia beſtia crudeliſſima,</hi> wrath ſaith hee, is a moſte cruell Beaſt, renting and tearing with her teeth: conſonant with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19429:13"/> our Prophet in this place. With whome accordeth Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> in a Sermon of this argument, comparing it to the ſwelling Waters, of which our Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh. <hi>The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent forces of men inraged with furie, carrie</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>all things before them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> like floods and inundations.</hi> Such a fire, ſuch a Beaſt, ſuch a ſwelling water is wrath in a man, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therewith: it conſumeth, it deuoureth, it ouer-whel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth al things, and therefore no meruaile, when the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is ſo bitter, if the ſtreames iſſuing from thence, bee ſo vnpleaſant as hath beene declared.</p>
            <p>Yet becauſe as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerueth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fourth to the <hi>Epheſians; Ira motus eſt naturalis conceptus ex cauſis,</hi> anger is a naturall motion, or commotion rather, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon ſome cauſe: Let vs conſider the cauſe, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated the aduerſaries of the people of Iſrael in ſuch ſort, as the Prophet in this Pſal. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth. A learned mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern expoſiter,<note place="margin">Wolf. Muſcul.</note> rendreth this reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it: that Iſrael hauing obtained a king of the Lord, that went in and out before them; they would no longer put their necks and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, vnder the yoake of their enemies; who before that time had dominion ouer them: vpon this defection, they make out after them with their forces, purſuing them in hoſtile manner to reduce them to their wonted ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had dealt with them in former times.</p>
            <p>A liuely Type of the aduerſaries of Gods Church in all ages, wherein wee may plainly ſee, what hath cauſed them from time to time to purſue Chriſt his members, with ſuch deadly wrath and hatred. It is, becauſe vpon the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Angell,<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.4. 2. Cor. 6.14</note> they are gone out of Babilon; or to ſpeake with the Apoſtle, becauſe they will not, <hi>iugumduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cum infidelibus,</hi> bee yoaked with Infidels and Heretikes in their errors and ſuperſtitions, hauing obtained a <hi>Dauid</hi> a King of God his Sonne Chriſt, that holy one, the Lords annointed.</p>
            <p>For if there bee any thing in the world that dooth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke a man and kindle his affections, it is Religion which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19429:13"/> maketh him not only defend to the vttermoſt of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and with his beſt endeuours, what he conceiueth to be pure, but alſo to proſecute with all might and furie, the contrarie ſect, to the vtter extinguiſhing and rooting vp of it, ſuppoſing that in ſo dooing, they fight Gods bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes. Hence proceeded that deadly fewd betweene the Hebrewes and the Egiptians;<note place="margin">Gen 43.32</note> they might not eate toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that was an abomination vnto them: between the Iewes and the <hi>Samaritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.9.</note> they medled not one with the other. The Poet obſerued as much among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
            <q>Immortale odium, &amp; nunquam ſanabile vulnus.<note place="margin">Inuenal. Satyr. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>Hatred without end, and a breach which neuer could bee cured.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Quum ſolos credat habendos</l>
               <l>Eſſe deos, quos ipſe colit.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Becauſe euerie nation beleeued thoſe onely to bee Gods whome they worſhipped. And <hi>Iulian</hi> noted it amongſt the chriſtians, as <hi>Amnianus Marcellinus</hi> reporteth: who found, he ſaid, no beaſts ſo deadly one to another, as Chriſtians were to Chriſtians: which beeing ſpoken by ſo great an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, as was that Apoſtate, would carrie little credit with it, were it not that the hiſtories of the Church recorded as much of the <hi>Nouatians,</hi> the <hi>Arrians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 22.</note> the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and ſuch like Heretikes againſt the Catholikes; whome impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience as <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> noteth, <hi>ad hoſtili a &amp; furioſa odia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulit,</hi> prouoked and forced to furious out-rage and deadly hatred.</p>
            <p>Heere was that Sword, of which our Sauiour fore-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Mat. 10.34. <hi>Thinke not that I come to ſend peace into the earth, I came not to ſend peace, but the ſword:</hi> whoſe part, Chriſt his Vicar thinketh hee plaieth not well, if hee bee not euer now &amp; then ſending abroad his ſword into pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant kingdomes, becauſe both Prince and people, are in his cenſure no better then forlorne Heretikes, paſt all hope of recouerie and amendment.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19429:14"/>
            <p>To which greeuous imputation wee anſwer with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that after this way which his holineſſe is pleaſed to call Hereſie, <hi>wee ſo worſhip the God of our Fathers, beleeuing all things which are written in the Law and the Prophets;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.14.</note> yea moreouer in the Euangeliſts &amp; Apoſtles, to whoſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if hee will ſtand, wee will eaſily lay this crime vppon himſelfe; in departing from the truth of that Goſpell, which not only <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, but our Sauiour and his Apoſtles preached.</p>
            <p>I will not now anotomize, and rip vp the whole body of popiſh ſuperſtition; wherein nature is oppoſed to grace; Saints merits to Chriſts his blood; their mediation to his interceſſion; vnwritten vanities, to the written truth, works to faith, with many ſuch like will-worſhips, which are after the doctrines of men: let the tryal be made in one point; the miſunderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding wherof ſo much troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Chriſtian world: I meane the natural &amp; ciuil obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of dutiful ſubiects towards their lawful princes.</p>
            <p>A duetie enioyned by our Sauiour. Mat. 22.22. <hi>Giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars:</hi> and ſeconded by that choſen veſſell, the Apoſtle of the Gentles, Rom. 13.7. <hi>Giue to all men their duetie, tribute to whome you owe tribute, cuſtome to whome cuſtome, feare to whome feare, honour to whome you owe honour.</hi> Whence are thoſe graue and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exhortations of the holy Apoſtle Saint Peter. 1.2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelues to all manner ordinance of men for the Lords ſake, whether it bee to the King as vnto the Superior, &amp;c</hi> and of <hi>S. Paul, Let euerie Soule be Subiect vnto the higher powers, Rom.</hi> 13.1. The reaſon of both, is worthy to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauen in the heart of the ſubiect with the point of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond: for the Lords ſake ſaith Saint Peter; for there is no power but of God, ſaith Saint Paul, with whome concurre the Law and the Prophets; the ancient Fathers of the Church, both in their writings, and in their meetings in generall counſell: which might as eaſily bee alleged if neede required.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19429:14"/>
            <p>But our Aduerſarie acknowledgeth as much, as he doth vs to wit in his letter; namely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 16.50.</note> that <hi>Subiects are bound to obey their Temporall Princes in all things lawfull; and thoſe not only good Princes, but had alſo; and that not only of feare and flatterie, but of conſcience,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teacheth, <hi>Propter conſcientiam, for conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why then ioine we not, as in tongue, ſo in hand and heart alſo, and admit the triall of our obedience by the touch-ſtone of true fidelitie, in taking the Oath of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 14.15.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 50.</note> Becauſe (ſaith our <hi>Engliſh Catholike) beſides the exaction of naturall obedience which is lawfull, the Oath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth diuers other points alſo, concerning matters of Catholike Religion, which are vnlawfull.</hi> For whereas <hi>the Oath is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into</hi> 14. <hi>ſeuerall parts,</hi> 12. <hi>of them at the leaſt</hi> (as hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoucheth) <hi>touch the Popes ſupremacie one way or other.</hi> As where it is ſaid in the Oath, that <hi>the Pope hath no authoritie to depoſe our King,</hi> 2. <hi>to diſpoſe of his Kingdomes,</hi> 3. <hi>to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize any forraine Prince to inuade or anoy him or his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> 4. <hi>or to diſcharge his ſubiects of their Allegeance,</hi> 5. <hi>to giue licence to any of them to beare armes againſt him,</hi> 6. <hi>or to offer violence to his perſon, or gouernment, or Subiects,</hi> The aſſertion of all which points, and other ſuch like ſpecified in the Oath, <hi>are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>matters of Catholike Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who ſeeth not (whoſe eies God hath opened to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the light of his Goſpell) that this Religion falſly ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Catholike,</hi> vtterly peruerteth the lawfull ſubiection of people to their Souereignes; and that Hell is not more oppoſite to Heauen, then the bearing of armes by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt his Prince, raiſing tumults in his dominions, offering violence to his perſon, ſtate, or gouernment, is contrarie to his allegeance and fidelitie? Chriſt (ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> in his Commentaries vpon the 13. to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi>) made nor Lawes, to ouerthrow the ſtate of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales, but that he might the better order and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them: but to depoſe Kings, to diſpoſe of their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to take the Crowne from one, and giue it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19429:15"/> as men toſſe a tenice ball in the Court, from <hi>Henrie</hi> to <hi>Rodulph,</hi> and ſo along; to aſſoile ſubiects of their fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; theſe and ſuch like, which are after the decrees of latter Popes, ouerthrow the very foundations of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Common-weales: which tranſcendent autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, whil'ſt they aſſume vnto themſelues, by vertue of the Churches cenſure, they goe farre beyond the bounds and limits of their commiſſion.</p>
            <p>For excommunication, being a puniſhment meerely ſpirituall, depriueth a man onely of ſuch ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, as otherwiſe he ſhould receiue at the hands of the Church: but no way impeacheth his eſtate in his goods and poſſeſſions;<note place="margin">De Iure &amp; iuſti. li. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Concluſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> as their owne <hi>Soto</hi> teacheth. And much leſſe hath it any force to depoſe Princes from their thrones, to abſolue ſubiects from their obedience, to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant them to rebell, to ſay violent-hands vpon their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereignes, or any way to conſpire, or worke their death.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, let this bee the obedience of ſuch Popiſh Recuſants as refuſe to profeſſe their fidelitie by taking the Oath;<note place="margin">Bulla Pij <hi>5.</hi> &amp; Gregorij <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> outwardly to make a ſhew of it, <hi>ad redimendam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xationem,</hi> to keepe themſelues from troubles and mulcts; yet with theſe circumſtances: 1. <hi>Rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> the State ſtanding ſo firme, as (God haue the glorie and praiſe for it) it doth: ſuch an vnion and conſent in Prince, Peeres, and all good Subiects, as need not dread the face of all their enemies: and 2. <hi>Donec publica Bullae executio fieri poſſit,</hi> that is, vntill they haue got ſtrength enough to make head againſt their Souereigne: and then downe with him, by open hoſtilitie, or ſecret conſpiracie, it maketh no matter which, ſo they haue their watch-word from <hi>Rome</hi> by the Popes excommunication and depoſing of him. But for vs, beloued, which haue otherwiſe learned Chriſt, let theſe ſeeds of diſloyaltie and treaſon bee farre from our hearts: Let vs giue to our <hi>Caeſar</hi> his feare, his honour, his ſeruice, his protection, by our bodies, goods, and liues; which are his, were he as wicked as was euer <hi>Nero:</hi> how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19429:15"/> much more, being ſo good and gratious, ſo zealous of Gods honour and of his ſubiects good: <hi>Neque enim pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſubuertic iſta ſubiectio;</hi> this ſubiection (ſaith <hi>S. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>) ſubuerteth not pietie; nay it confirmeth it more. Neither is this ſpirituall, but ciuill obedience, due to the Prince ordained by God; not depending vpon the Pope, who exalteth his owne ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Were he placed in his due ranke, <hi>Siue Apoſtolus,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> were he an Apoſtle, that is, as good as <hi>S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himſelf, or were he an Euangeliſt, or were he a Prophet; he were but a Subiect: or if all this ſerue not, the next words immediately enſuing will order him; <hi>Siue quiſ quis fuerit,</hi> or be he what he will be or may be, ſaith <hi>S. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, if he conſiſt of a ſoule and body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>he muſt be ſubiect to the higher Poxers,</hi> that is, to the King, or to the Emperour, Gods viue images vpon earth; and acknowledge them for his Lords,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 32.</note> as <hi>Pope Gregorie</hi> the great did <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperor.</p>
            <p>Or if theſe bee matters which concerne Religion, and ſuch as touch the Popes Supremacie ſpirituall, why doth not our <hi>Engliſh Catholike</hi> bring foorth his proofes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially hauing made promiſe ſo to doe, in the fore-front of his Pamphlet? But open it, and peruſe it from the firſt page to the laſt, you ſhall finde nothing therein, but his owne aſſertion; <hi>the Popes ſuppoſition,</hi> or at the moſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 13. 14. 15. 50. 62. 74. 85.</note> his <hi>determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; the authoritie of Cardinall Bellarmine; and the chiefeſt learned men of their Church,</hi> as he tearmeth them: that is, <hi>Herod and Pilate, the high Prieſts and Elders, the Scribes and Phariſeis, with the nation of the Iewes,</hi> conſpiring againſt our Sauiour, and ſeeking falſe witneſſes againſt him, but finding none. For no better with vs is the credit of the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Conſiſtorie,</hi> his College of <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and the whole ſwarmes of his <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Friars,</hi> in matters concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their owne authoritie, contrary to the expreſſe words of holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>Yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 14.19.85.</note> but if the Pope haue not this authoritie to proceed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19429:16"/> againſt Princes, by <hi>dethroning</hi> and <hi>depoſing</hi> of them, for their reſtraint and amendment, Gods prouidence ſhould be defectuous (ſaith our <hi>Engliſh Catholike</hi>) for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his Church. I anſwer; Nothing leſſe. For if <hi>S. Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors were able to gouerne the Church in the middeſt of al the ſtormes of perſecutions vnder the <hi>Pagan Emperors</hi> (who laboured by all cruell meanes to root out the very name of Chriſtianitie) without the vſe of any ſuch authoritie; how much more eaſie muſt it bee for them who claime ſucceſſion from <hi>S. Peter,</hi> to gouerne the ſhip of the Church, when by the commandement of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> the windes are ceaſed, and the ſtormes are laied? Vnleſſe wee ſhall ſay, that the Church had not her due gouernment, but was toſſed vp and downe with euery waue and puffe of winde, for the ſpace of 1000. yeeres and vpward after Chriſt, vntill ſuch time as <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, lifted vp his Prieſtly launce (as they ſay) againſt <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſword, and vſurped the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of decrowning Princes. Which were abſurd, once to enter into any mans conceit of common ſenſe or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Yet more then this our <hi>Engliſh Catholike</hi> ſaith not.</p>
            <p>But perchance <hi>Matthew Tort, Cardinall Bellarmines Chaplaine,</hi> prooueth the point more ſubſtantially. True, if the wreſting of a place or two in holy Scripture make any thing to the purpoſe. He allegeth out of <hi>Iohn</hi> 21.15.16. our Sauiour his charge to <hi>S. Peter, Feed my Lambes, Feed my ſheepe:</hi> And out of <hi>S. Matthew, c.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 19. the like ſaying to <hi>S. Peter, I will giue vnto thee the Keies of the Kingdome of Heauen: and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde vpon earth, ſhall be bound in heauen; and whatſoeuer thou ſhalt looſe vpon earth, ſhall be looſed in heauen.</hi> From whence (ſaith he) <hi>omnes Catholici colligunt,</hi> all <hi>Catholikes</hi> doe gather, that it appertaineth to the authoritie of the high Biſhop (hee meaneth the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) not onely to haue power to looſe from ſinnes, <hi>ſed etiam à poenis, cenſuris, legibus, votis, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iuramentis,</hi> but from puniſhments, Cenſures, Lawes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19429:16"/> vowes and Othes, <hi>When it ſhall make for Gods glorie and the Saluation of ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when, may this <hi>[when]</hi> euer bee; that God ſhall bee glorified, by ouerthrowing all lawes, both diuine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane? or is any thing more impoſſible, then that truth ſhould receiue honour from lying &amp; periuries? Is not this to make a lie for God, which holy Iob ſo much deteſteth c. 13. ve. 9. Or in the beſt ſenſe to do euill, <hi>that good may come therby?</hi> which whoſoeuer ſhal atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, the Apoſtle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth of them, that their damnation is iuſt. Ro. 3.8.</p>
            <p>Againe, where the Chaplaine auoucheth his expoſition of looſing to bee ment, not onely of remiſſion of ſinnes, (which wee willingly acknowledge with his Lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Cardinal) but alſo of relaxation, from lawes,<note place="margin">de Rom. pontifi lib. <hi>1.</hi> C. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> vows and oathes, from the authoritie of all Catholikes <hi>(omnes Catholici colligunt:)</hi> either the ancient Fathers of the Church,<note n="a" place="margin">In Mathae.</note> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">In Pſal. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Aduerſus. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiu. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierome,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">In I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha. tract <hi>118.</hi> &amp; de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon. Chriſti. Ca. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Angustine</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">De Trinit. l. <hi>6</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Chryſost. de ſacerdot. lib. <hi>2</hi> Theophilact in Mat. cap. <hi>16</hi> Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de vnit Eccleſiaeſeu de ſimplicitat. praelatorem. Anſel. in Mat c. <hi>16.</hi> ver. <hi>19.</hi> Beda ibid. &amp;c.</note> ſuch like are no Catholikes; or elſe hee fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that vpon them, which neuer came within compaſſe of their thoughts.</p>
            <p>Who moreouer ioyntly teach and profeſſe, that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>binding and looſing, and feeding Chriſt his Sheepe,</hi> was by our Sauiour giuen as well to the reſt of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as vnto <hi>Peter;</hi> that <hi>they all receiued the Keyes as well as Peter; what was ſaid to Peter was ſaid to all, the promiſe to Peter was common to all:</hi> they are the expreſſe words of theſe Fathers. So that as yet neither our Engliſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, nor the Cardinals Chaplaine haue ſaid any thing to prooue, that the authoritie of <hi>binding &amp; looſing, and feeding Chriſt his Sheepe,</hi> belongeth more to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſors, then to the other Apoſtles and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors; or that the Depoſing of princes is a point of Doctrine belonging to the Popes ſupremacie, more then to the Supremacie of other Patriarkes; and much leſſe that it is a matter of Catholike, that is, Apoſtolike or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, for Subiects in any caſe at his command
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19429:17"/> to beare armes againſt their Soueraigne, or to attempt any thing againſt his ſtate and perſon.</p>
            <p>By this which hath beene deliuered, I hope it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, not only how repugnant the voice of that Antichriſt of Rome is to the voice of chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles, in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull obedience of Subiects towards their Soueraigne: but alſo how pernicious Popiſh Doctrine is to States and Kingdomes, depoſing Princes from their Throanes, and arming their Subiects againſt them.</p>
            <p>And therefore howſoeuer the Engliſh Catholike in his Letter auerreth,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> that <hi>libertie of Conſcience</hi> (hee meaneth in Popiſh Religion) <hi>ought to bee as free in this Kingdome, as breathing, and the vſe of the aire is common to all:</hi> yet the wiſdome of our <hi>Solomon</hi> dooth ſee, that as one Temple could not containe Gods Ark and Dagon;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.3.4. 2. Cor. 6.14.15</note> as light hath no communion with darkenes; Chriſt no concord with <hi>Beli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;</hi> ſo neither can the puritie of the Goſpell haue any agreement with Popiſh Superſtition.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour himſelfe hath deliuered his iudgement in this caſe. Mat. 12.25. <hi>Euerie kingdome deuided againſt it ſelf ſhall bee brought to naught; and euerie Cittie or houſe deuided againſt it ſelf ſhall not ſtand.</hi> And what greater diuiſion then this can be thought in a ſtate &amp; kingdom, then where Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tate is oppoſed to Potentate? the Pope againſt the king: Subiect againſt Subiect: Seruant againſt Seruant: both walking diuers waies, after diuers Maſters. Such diuiſions of hearts &amp; affections, cannot but prooue deadly in the end to the body, wherein they ſhall bee found, bee it ciuill or Eccleſiaſtical, Church or Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>From hence proceed wrath, enuyings, ſeditions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions,<note place="margin">Dion. Caſſ.</note> murthers; as <hi>Mecaenas</hi> long ſince tolde <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperor. You may take it from a latter writer; whoſe teſtimonie is beyond all exception, as beeing an enemie; and therefore likely to aduiſe vs no more for our good, then what the force of truth wreſteth from him. It is <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> the Diuinitie profeſſor in the Engliſh Colledge at <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19429:17"/> lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de triplici hominis Officio. ca.</hi> 14. <hi>If, ſaith he, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple conceiue an opinion of their King to bee an enemie to their Religion, or to contemne it; what is there that they will not attempt againſt his life, to the effuſion of his blood, iubente religione, &amp; impelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te cos de ſuper numine, vti omnino apud ſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimis firmabunt.</hi> Religion commanding them, and the God, whom they worſhip, forcing them therunto, as they are perſwaded in their conſciences.</p>
            <p>Could hee more liuely haue deſcribed our Ieſuited Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, <hi>Whoſe Religion is rebellion, and murthering of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> eſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Lord God the Pope,<note place="margin">Gloſ. in cap. Cum inter. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trauag. Ioa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>22</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>dominus Deus noſter Papa</hi> (yee know whoſe ſaying it is) ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and exhort them thereunto? And againe, in the concluſion of the Chapter. <hi>Whoſoeuer</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſhall conſider the infinite hatred, which from time to time, hath paſſed betweene Heretikes and Catholikes, ſhall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceiue that it cannot stand with ciuill Policie, that ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſuch contrarie opinions in Religion, ſhould bee fitly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned in the ſame ciuill ſocietie; and that the ſafetie of the Prince cannot ſuffer ſuch promiſcuous conuenticles, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed manners of worſhip in Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Engliſh Catholike acknowledgeth as much in his Letter: adding further, that <hi>beſides internall dangers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 124.</note> 
               <hi>which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are euer conſequent vpon ſuch inward diuiſions of Religion; if forreine occaſions ſhould be offered vs againe (as in former times they haue beene, by forraine warres) wee ſhould not know how to truſt the one the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere is plaine dealing indeede, you heare him now ſpeake plainely, laying aſide his vſuall manner of cogging and Aequiuocating: and is there not, iudge ye, great cauſe, that libertie of their conſcience &amp; Religion, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſuch dangers both to Prince and Countrie, ſhould be as common <hi>amongſt vs in this Kingdome, as the vſe of the aire &amp; breathing is common to all?</hi> or rather is there not great neede that the Statutes concerning obſtinate Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, were put more duely in execution, and not lie ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19429:18"/> ſo much as they doe in the ſcabbard? &amp; that all loyall ſubiects were ſealed like the Seruants of God in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads: making open profeſſion by their Oath of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull allegeance towards their Soueraigne,<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.3.</note> which in a cauſe ſo conformable to Gods will and command; ſo behooufull to church and common-wealth; ſo neerely touching Gods glorie, the peace, ſafetie and honour both of Prince and People: whoſoeuer ſhould refuſe, I wiſh his legs ſo fettered, though not with giues of yron, and his armes ſo weakned, though not by drawing one drop of blood; that theſe Serpents might not bee able to ſting, when they moſt deſired; nor theſe Wolues to prey vpon vs when they moſt longed.</p>
            <p>Thus yee haue the roote from whence ſpring theſe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fruits of ſubtiltie and crueltie in the Aduerſaries of the church; their wrath kindled not vpon a light &amp; friuolous occaſion, but burning with the zeale of Religion, though a zeale not according to knowledge, and religion without due feare of God, and reuerence of man.</p>
            <p>There remaine yet two points vnhandled: the one, of the deliuerance of the Church from her enemies: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of the duetie of praiſe, &amp; thankſ-giuing to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for this deliuerance: which (the time beeing ſo ready to preuent me, and my voice failing) I will fould vp in a word, by way of application to our ſelues: whome as God hath made examples of his mightie power, no nation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen more, in deliuering vs out of the hands of all our enemies, both from the Snares of ſecret treacheries, and from the open violence of their intended cruelties: ſo there is no people in the world more obliged to the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of praiſe and thankeſ-giuing to the Lord.</p>
            <p>I will not now ſtand to repeate vnto you our former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance; that <hi>mirabilis Annus</hi> the yere 88. ſo long before ſpoken of, for the wondrous effects which it was expected it ſhould produce: it ſuffiſeth, that it was wonderful to vs, when ſtanding, as it were ſtill, wee ſaw the ſaluation of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19429:18"/> 
               <hi>Lord,</hi> fighting his and our battailes, againſt theſe, his and our enemies; and chaſing them, vntill he had made almoſt a finall end of them, whom the Pope had bleſſed, with the name of inuincible.</p>
            <p>Neither will I call to your mindes the manifold dangers and treacheries, ſo oft plotted againſt our late gratious Souereigne, and in her life, againſt ours: with which our moſt noble King that now raigneth, hath beene as freſhly aſſaulted, ſithence his entrance into his Throane and Kingdome: of all which, we may ſay with the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>From them all the Lord hath deliuered vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider but this day, the birth-day, as I may tearme it, of our Country; in which both Prince and people came as it were anew into the world, deliuered from the dreadfull Powder-vault, the very belly of hell and confuſion,<note place="margin">C. 2.10.</note> as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> ſometime did from the belly of the Whale.</p>
            <p>How deſperate and bloody was the attempt? How ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly was the ſnare laid to entrap vs vnawares? When euery man ſung to his neighbor, nothing but <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> how neere were we brought to the pits brinke? I ſay not as <hi>Ionah</hi> did, Yet 40. daies; but yet, not ſo much as one day,<note place="margin">C. 3.4.</note> and we ſhould haue beene deſtroied: when being ready to ſinke, God ſtretched forth his hand vnto vs, as ſometimes he did to <hi>Peter,</hi> and tooke vs as <hi>a brand out of the fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 14.31. Zechar. 3.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Surely heere was neither want of malice, will, or ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the Aduerſarie, in ſpreading the net, that it preuailed not; nor force of wiſdome or deepe inſight in any that preuented it: the heart of our moſt wiſe and prudent King, how large ſoeuer it bee, as the waters which couer the ſea, yet was it at this time <hi>extraordinarily inſpired</hi> from aboue, when out of a cloud of <hi>darke ſpeeches,</hi> by the finger of God, he noted and pointed at the treacherie.</p>
            <p>And therefore more properly may we take vp this ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then euer did <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tremel. &amp; Iun.</note> who ſpake it but in a trope and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure: <hi>If the Lord had not beene on our ſide, may we of England ſay; if the Lord had not beene on our ſide, when men roſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19429:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> vs; they had then ſwallowed vs vp quicke, when their wrath was kindled againſt vs. But praiſed be the Lord, who gaue vs not ouer for a prey vnto their teeth. Our ſoule is eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as a bird out of the ſnare of the Fowlers;</hi> when our enemies fell into the pit of deſtruction, which they had digged for vs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, let the praiſes of God bee alwaies ſounding in our mouths, both of Prince and people, old and yong, men and maidens, women and children: let vs all in our places and callings, age and ſexes, praiſe the name of the Lord, which is only to be exalted; not wiſdome, ſtrength, or worthineſſe in our ſelues. And let others put their truſt in horſes and Chariots, in the multitude of their hoſts, in the ſtrength of their ſhips, in the Popes curſings and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; but let vs alwaies thinke and ſay, with our Prophet in the concluſion of this Pſalme, <hi>Our helpe is in the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which moſt glorious name be rendred all praiſe, honour and glory, might and Maieſtie, this day, and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19429:19"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>AT THE SPITTLE.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH.</hi> C. <hi>7.</hi> V. <hi>15.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Beware of falſe Prophets, which come to you in ſheepes cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but inwardly they are rauening Wolues.</p>
                  <p>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the manifold dangers, amidſt which the Arke of Gods Church is toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp and downe by the ſlie impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of her enemies, as by ſo many ſtormes and ſurges; the perils by falſe Prophets and ſeducing Teachers are ſuch, as if with diligent heed and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they be not auoided, as the Syrtes and Rockes of the Sea, we are in danger euery houre to make ſhipwracke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can ſo much as ſee the hauen, wherein our ſoules long ſo earneſtly to be at reſt.</p>
            <p>The greater is the vigilancie of Gods watchfull eie ouer his ſillie flocke; neuer ſlumbering nor ſleeping;<note place="margin">Pſal. 121.4.</note> but as a carefull father warning vs before hand of them, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets;</hi> and as a painfull maſter diligently inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs how we may know and auoid them: <hi>Yee ſhall know them by their fruits,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour: masked otherwiſe ſo with ſheepes-cloathing, as that by their outward ſhew and habit, they are able to deceiue, if it were poſſible, the very elect.</p>
            <p>For this ſheepes-cloathing is that external habit, which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19429:20"/> naturally and properly belonging to the ſheepe, maketh vs take them to be ſo, which come ſo clad vnto vs. It is, ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">De praeſcript. Haeretic. Caluin. Janſen.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian, nominis Chriſtiani extrinſecus ſuperficies the ſuperficiall outſide of a Chriſtian;</hi> that is, holineſſe, but feined; pietie and Religion, but in ſhew: it is<note n="b" place="margin">Author ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris imperfecti, in Matt. hom. <hi>19.</hi> Lucas Burgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>vestimentum ouile, the ſheepes skinne</hi> indeed, his wooll, his fleeſe, his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward apparance and reſemblance: but it is not <hi>Opus ouile, the true ſheepes deed,</hi> his naturall worke; the Religion is not pure, the holineſſe not ſincere and vpright: which yet notwithſtanding dazleth our eies, and peruerteth our iudgement, if we be not very wary and circumſpect.</p>
            <p>Therefore our Sauiour willeth vs, not to ſtand at gaze, and to looke vpon them; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith he, heed them, marke them, eie them well; which is, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Maſters meaning, <hi>Beleeue not euery ſpirit, but trie the ſpirits whether they are of God,</hi> 1.4.1. A point of skill, beyond the reach of <hi>Babes, who being inexpert in the word, vſe milke</hi> (ſuch as they were, whom the Author to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes</hi> therefore reprooueth for it, c. 5. v. 12.13. and as the Lay people are in the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> whoſe faith lieth foulded vp in the faith of the Church,<note place="margin">Fides impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita.</note> without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch and enquirie:) it is the part of ſtronger men; yet not of the Paſtor and Doctor alone, as<note n="c" place="margin">Promptuar. Cathol. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic <hi>7.</hi> poſt Pentecoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Stapleton</hi> would haue it; but of the flocke too, <hi>which through long cuſtome haue their wits exerciſed, to diſcerne both good &amp; euill, Heb</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Author operis imperfecti, in Mat. hom. 19.</note>
               <hi>Magna virtus boni, malum cognoſcere: Heere is a ſpeciall vertue and propertie peculiar to goodneſſe it ſelfe, to diſcerne that which is euill:</hi> and, <hi>firma tutela ſalutis, ſcire quem fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as; a ſure defenſe preſeruatiue of our welfare, to know him whom thou muſt eſchew and auoid:</hi> which that wee may bee able to performe, our Sauiour addeth<note n="d" place="margin">Lucas Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſ. Maldo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat.</note> 
               <hi>Symbolum,</hi> a badge or cognizance, though not <hi>a Priore</hi> (for God onely is<note n="e" place="margin">Act. c. 1. v. 24.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſearcher of the hearts and reines) yet <hi>a Poſteriore,</hi> a ſigne better ſuting with our vnderſtanding, from the effect; <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them. Per hoc
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19429:20"/> quod foris agitur, quicquid intus lat et aperitur, that which lieth hid within the heart, is made manifeſt</hi> (ſaith<note n="f" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ral. l. <hi>15</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie) by that which a man dooth without: as in the Water a face anſwereth to the face</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) Prouerb.</hi> 27. <hi>verſe</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>And what are theſe fruits? The<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 19.</note> author of the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect worke vpon Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> his Goſpell, reſolueth the doubt verie fitly in two words. <hi>Fructus hominis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>confeſſio fidei eius, &amp; opera conuerſationis ipſius: the fruits wherby a man is knowne,</hi> the true Prophet is diſcerned from the falſe, the ſheepe from the Wolfe; are the confeſſion of his Faith, and his life and conuerſation. For if a man hide the Wolfe vnder the ſheepes-cloathing, how canſt thou know him, ſaith the ſame author,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.47.</note> 
               <hi>niſi aut per vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem, aut per actionem: but by his voice or by his deedes? Si con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio eius conueniat cum ſcripturis,</hi> if his confeſſion be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the Scriptures, if his life anſwerable to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>verus Chriſtianus eſt, this man indeede is an Iſraelite, in whome is no guile:</hi> if otherwiſe, <hi>falſus Propheta eſt,</hi> it is the Wolfe vnder the ſheepes-cloathing, ſhunne him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of him.</p>
            <p>So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue in the word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read vnto you, firſt a Caueat like a Pharos, ſet at the entrie of my text,<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> to giue light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, <hi>beware.</hi> Secondly the Rockes and <hi>Syrtes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which wee are to ſhunne, <hi>falſe Prophets.</hi> Thirdly, a reaſon of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, their diſguiſed masking of themſelues, becauſe <hi>they come to you in ſheepes-cloathing, but inwardly are rauening Wolues.</hi> Laſtly, the markes and tokens whereby yee may diſcrie and diſcerne them, <hi>yee ſhall know them by their fruits.</hi> Which being the verie foundation of all the reſt, my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and time ſhall bee ſpent, (by Gods gracious aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and your wonted patience) in laying open of them: which being diſcloſed, the reſt of it ſelfe will fall to the ground, it beeing an eaſie matter to beware of the Wolfe, when hee is ſtripped of his ſheepes-cloathing.</p>
            <p>Yet the caſe ſo ſtanding, as<note n="h" place="margin">Homil. de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaritia. tom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſostome</hi> doth truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it: <hi>multa ouium vellera, innumeri vbi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> lupi ſub his oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultati;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:19429:21"/> that <hi>there are many Sheepe-skins,</hi> &amp; as many Wolues that lie hid vnder them: and that many falſe Prophets, vnder colour of the true, haue in all ages crept into Chriſt his flocke: wee muſt heerein alſo vſe a moderation: and out of many ſortes, make choice of ſome, by which you may iudge of the reſt.</p>
            <p>And becauſe euerie one as he is iealous of his reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: laboureth to remooue this imputation from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; the<note n="i" place="margin">Huiuſmodi ſunt Coluiniſtae Maldonat. Stapleto. Ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>benus de falſis propheti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Papiſts falſelie charging vs with it; and wee lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, as the truth is, &amp; where it is to be found, vpon them: wee will heerein follow the aduiſe of<note n="k" place="margin">In Mar. c <hi>7.</hi> verſ. <hi>15.16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ferus</hi> one of their Friars: laying aſide our owne aſſeuerations, wee will name an Arbitrator betweene vs, to decide this controuerſie; <hi>Scriptura iudex ſit, let the Scripture</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>be the iudge, quem illa falſum Prophetam nominat, is procul dubio talis ſit;</hi> whome the <hi>Scripture ſhall ſay to bee the falſe Prophet, let him bee ſo reputed and accounted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the inſtance to make tryall by (to limit my ſelfe within ſome bounds) I will put infoure points. The firſt, concerning traditions. The ſecond in worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages. The third in Miracles; all matters of Doctrine as yee know, and controuerted betweene vs and our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries the Papiſts, and belonging to the voice of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: the firſt principall fruite, by which hee is knowne: the fourth and laſt, concerning manners and life; which are his deedes and actions, the other principall fruite, of which our Sauiour hath pronounced, <hi>by their fruites yee ſhall know them.</hi> By theſe ye may make an eſtimate of the reſt, and accordingly iudge of the true &amp; falſe Prophets.</p>
            <p>Firſt then to beginne with that, which is the foundation of many others. Our Sauiour (ſaith <hi>Ferus</hi>) calleth them falſe Prophets, Mat. 15.3. <hi>which tranſgreſſe the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God by their traditions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. in c. <hi>7.</hi> Mat.</note> For theſe. Mat. cap. 23.16. hee calleth for the ſame cauſe, <hi>Blinde Guides, which are all one with falſe Prophets,</hi> and denounceth a <hi>vae</hi> againſt them, <hi>Woe be vnto you blinde guides.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19429:21"/>
            <p>Now this is an eſſentiall propertie of the <hi>Guides and doctors</hi> of the Romiſh <hi>Synagog;</hi> who not contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with <hi>the fountaines of liuing waters, the holy Scriptures and word of God,</hi> as not <hi>containing all things ſufficient for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this life, and Saluation in that which is to come,</hi> dig to themſelue <hi>pits, euen broken pits</hi> of diuers and ſundrie tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which in truth can holde no water.</p>
            <p>For thus<note n="m" place="margin">Bellarmine de verbo dei. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> they teach and profeſſe, that beſides the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word of God, there is an other part thereof not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten (their meaning is in the Scriptures) and <hi>by the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors therof, the Apoſtles of our Sauiour, though otherwiſe it be exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, almoſt in the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Fathers,</hi> (<note n="n" place="margin">Bellarmine.</note> as they ſay) which they tearme &amp; call traditions, of which they make many ſorts; agreeing in this, that they concerne both faith &amp; maners.</p>
            <p>What reckoning and account they make of theſe tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſhall come from their owne mouthes: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it would ſeeme, I ſuppoſe, incredible, what they aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be vnto them.</p>
            <p>The<note n="o" place="margin">Pari pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis affectu et reuerentia ſeſ. <hi>4.</hi> decret. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> decreeth, that <hi>they are to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with the like affection of Godlineſſe and reuerence, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee admit and reuerence the bookes of the old and new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vim habent. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo dei. li. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, <hi>that they haue all one Force and ſtrength.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Perinde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> auct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritatem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent. Analiſ. fidei Cathol. li. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> ſec. <hi>2:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Valentia; the authoritie of each is alike infallible, and cannot deceiue.</hi> Cardinall <hi>Hoſsius</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Multo max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ima pars euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelij, peruenit ad nos traditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne per ex igua literis eſt mandata. confeſſ. Catholica. c. <hi>92.</hi>
               </note> not content with this paritie, addeth further, that <hi>far the greateſt part of the Goſpel came to vs by traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when</hi> but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie little thereof was committed to writing. And<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ex traditione noui teſtamenti ſcripta omnia authoritatem acceperunt. Annal. <hi>46.1.</hi> Ann. <hi>53.</hi> num. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> Cardinal <hi>Baronius,</hi> as if this were not enough, auoucheth, that <hi>all the bookes of the new Teſtament, receiue their authoritie from traditions.</hi> In regard whereof hee preferreth them before the Scriptures; becauſe Scriptures, ſaith he, <hi>vnleſſe they be eſtabliſhed by traditions, haue no beeing: when as traditions without the Scripture, are firme and ſtable in themſelues.</hi> So<note n="t" place="margin">Scripturae niſi traditione firmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non ſubſistunt, traditiones vero ſine ſcriptis, ſuam obtinent firmitatem.</note>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:19429:22"/> likewiſe <hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Petrus</hi> a Soto before him,<note n="r" place="margin">Fundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; explicatio defenſ. Cathol. confeſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>68</hi>
               </note> calleth <hi>them the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and expoſition of the Scriptures:</hi> And<note n="u" place="margin">Lydius lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Panopl. li. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lindane, the touchſtone of true and falſe doctrine.</hi> Finally, <hi>Andradius</hi> ſaith, <hi>That many points and heads of Faith, would reele and totter, were they not ſupported by the aſſiſtance and authority of tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Multa ſidei noſtrae capita reperies nutare iam et vacilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſi tollas tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionum ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium et aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox. Explicat. l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>80.</hi>
               </note> yea not onely reele and totter, <hi>but a great part of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion would alſo periſh</hi> (ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">Sine quibus magna pars re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis perit, et ad inane no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um redit. de. ſenſ. Cathol. l. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>68.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Soto) were it not for thoſe partes of Doctrine, which are maintained by tradition; and the Goſpell would come to a vaine name, without ſubſtance;</hi> which I eaſily grant and acknowledge, in their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Faith and Religion, which can no more ſtand without traditions, then a huge building without a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</p>
            <p>For it is the confeſſion proceeding from their owne mouthes, that the Primacie of the Pope, and Sea-Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like is from tradition; their fiue Sacraments of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Order and Matrimonie, Penance, extreame vnction, with their elements, words, fruites, and effects; the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of water and oile in the ſacrament of Baptiſme; The Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and receiuing in one kinde; of auricular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, ſatisfaction, choiſe of meats, Faſtes purgatorie, monaſtical profeſſion, ſingle life, praier for the dead,<note n="z" place="margin">Petrus a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vt ſupra. Pereſius de traditionibus parte. <hi>3.</hi> Lindanus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. li. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>100.</hi> Canus locor. Theologic. li. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>3. 4. 5. with the reſt.</hi>
               </note> inuocation and worſhipping of Saints, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping their Relikes and images; in a word, ſcantlie any matter in controuerſie betweene vs, which they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge not to bee grounded on tradition; howſoeuer with conſciences more then ſeared, in their diſputes they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage <hi>Scriptures for proofe of them; and</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In his Rock.</note> 
               <hi>Sanders proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that they haue moſte plaine Scriptures, in all points, for the Catholike Faith</hi> (falſely ſo called) and none at all againſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>The caſe then ſtanding thus with the Popiſh Religion, it is no maruell if ſo highly they extoll their traditions, and on the other ſide thinke and ſpeake ſo baſelie of the holy Scriptures, tearming them<note n="b" place="margin">Tilmannus. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhuſius ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. errores. Tit. de Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura. Sac.</note> 
               <hi>a noſe of Wax</hi> readie to receiue any impreſſion, expound it how a man liſt, a <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19429:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> rule,</hi> flexible and eaſie to bee wreſted, whither a man will; a <hi>dumbe teacher, which can neither anſwer nor expreſſe his owne meaning; a dead Scripture; the matter and ſubiect of ſtrife and contention: which without the Churches authoritie, is of no more credit then Aeſop his fables; yea a very bable,</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fulcke</hi> his confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Saunders</hi> treatiſe of the worſhipping of images, pag. 575.</note> 
               <hi>Doctor Cole</hi> the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> being <hi>Viſitor in Cambridge,</hi> when a <hi>Bible</hi> was brought vnto him to be defaced, called it <hi>Bible Bable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe blaſphemies againſt Gods ſacred word, which<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 1.16. 1. Cor. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth, <hi>the wiſdome of God, and the power of God vnto ſaluation, to euery one that beleeueth;</hi> demonſtrate theſe <hi>Popiſh Doctors</hi> (if I ſhould adde nothing more) to be thoſe <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> of which our Sauiour heere ſpeaketh. For right ſo did their fore-fathers, the ancient <hi>Heretikes, vilifie the holy Scriptures, and magnifie their Traditions,</hi> as<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> a moſtancient Father teſtifieth. <hi>Cùm ex Scripturis argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur, When</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>men argue againſt them, and they are reprooued out of the Scriptures, they turne themſelues to accuſe the Scriptures, quaſi non rectè habeant, as if they were not right, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſint ex authoritate, nor haue authoritie in them, &amp; quia ſint variè dictae, and becauſe they are diuerſly ſpoken, and haue diuers ſenſes, &amp; quia non poſſit ex his inueniri veritas, ab his qui neſciant Traditionem, and becauſe the truth cannot bee found nor gathered out of them by ſuch as know not the Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Non enim per literas traditam illam, ſed per viuam vocem. For</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the truth was not deliuered by writing, in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Scriptures; but by word of mouth, from man to man. Neuer</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Non tam o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum ouo ſimile Cicer. Acade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. quaeſ. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>was one egge ſo like another,</hi> as theſe <hi>old Heretikes</hi> and our <hi>Popiſh Doctors, Soto, Lindane, Pighius,</hi> and ſuch like of the Popiſh crew.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe are many of their reaſons and arguments, the dull and blunted weapons of the old <hi>Heretikes,</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon them ſo often by the ancient Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="g" place="margin">De verbo Dei, l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> allegeth, for proofe of his Traditions, that of our Sauiours, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>I haue yet many things to ſay vnto you, but yee cannot beare them now.</hi> With which ſaying
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19429:23"/> of Chriſts, all <hi>Heretikes, euen the moſt abſurd and fooliſh, which notwithſtanding would be called Chriſtians, did endeuour to colour</hi> (ſaith<note n="h" place="margin">Omnes inſipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiſſ haeretici, qui ſe Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos vocari vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, audacias figmentorum ſuorum, quas maximè exhorret ſenſus humanus, hac occaſione Euangelicae ſententiae colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e conantur. Jn Euang. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hann tract. <hi>97.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſtine) the audacious fictions of their idle braines, which the ſenſe of man did moſt of all feare and abhorre.</hi> But as that godly Father anſwereth, ſo ſay I; <hi>If our Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our concealed thoſe things, quis noſtrum dicat, iſta velilla ſunt? who is he amongst vs, that may ſay, they are this, or they are that.</hi> Yet<note n="i" place="margin">Haec multa non erant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa ab his, quae hactenus Dominus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens docuerat, ſed planior &amp; clarior eorum explicatio. Concordant. fol <hi>964.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ianſenius,</hi> one of their owne, well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, that <hi>theſe many things were not diuers and contrarie to thoſe which our Sauiour taught his Diſciples whil'ſt hee was preſent amongst them; but only a more full and cleerer explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So<note n="k" place="margin">Loc. theol. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Canus</hi> allegeth that of the Apoſtles; <hi>We ſpeake wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome amongst them that are perfect,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. whereby he would prooue, that <hi>certaine holy myſteries were communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Apoſtle, apart from the ignorant, to the perfect: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectis &amp; maioribus.</hi> Euen as the old <hi>Heretikes</hi> (ſaith<note n="l" place="margin">Hanc ſapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnuſquiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eorum eſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, quam à ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipſo ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenit, fictione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videlicet.</note> 
               <hi>Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>) by occaſion of theſe words of <hi>S Paul, Did euery one of them call the fiction of their owne b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine, this ſelfe ſame wiſdome of which the Apoſtle ſpake?</hi> But<note n="m" place="margin">Si quaedam inter domeſticos diſſerebant, non tamen ea fuiſſe credendum eſt, quae aliam regulam fidei ſuperducerent, &amp;c. De praeſcript. haeretic.</note> 
               <hi>Ianſenius</hi> rightly noteth,<note n="n" place="margin">Sed quod ſuae prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>otionis &amp; fidei myſteria perfectius aperiret perfectioribus, ſermonemque ſuum aptaret audientium capacitati. Concordant. f. <hi>965.</hi>
               </note> as did <hi>Tertullian</hi> before him, that the Apoſtle did not ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie by thoſe words, that <hi>he taught the perfect one thing, the vnperfect and ignorant another thing; cum vtriſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eandem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem praedicaret, when as he preached the ſame faith to them both:</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Sed quod ſuae prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>otionis &amp; fidei myſteria perfectius aperiret perfectioribus, ſermonemque ſuum aptaret audientium capacitati. Concordant. f. <hi>965.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but that his preaching was not all after one manner, which he applied to his hearers, to ſome more perfectly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly, to others after a plainer faſhion, according to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie of each of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, what the Apoſtle writeth to <hi>Timothie, O Timo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theus, keepe that which is committed vnto thee, depoſitum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodi,</hi> 1.6.20. is<note n="o" place="margin">Canus. Bellarmine. &amp;c.</note> generally alleged of them, for proofe of their Traditions. And ſo was it by the old <hi>Heretikes,</hi> as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19429:23"/>
               <note n="p" place="margin">De praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion. hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eticor.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> witneſſeth; who from thence taught, <hi>that the Apoſtles</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Apoſtolos non omnia omnibus tradidiſſe, ibid <hi>And</hi> non om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia omnibus reuelaſſe: quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam palam &amp; vniuerſis, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſecretò &amp; paucis deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſſe: quia &amp; hoc verbo vſus eſt Paulus ad Timotheum, O Timothee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ib.</note> 
               <hi>deliuered not all things to all ſorts of men, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome things openly and to all men; other matters ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and to few.</hi> But <hi>depoſitum,</hi> or the thing committed, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the whole charge which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> committed to <hi>Timothie,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Quod praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſupra &amp; infra ex ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis intelligerat, non neſcio quid oſtendi hoc dicto de remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiore doctrina, &amp;c. ib.</note> and particularly the true <hi>forme of ſound doctrine,</hi> deliuered vnto him in that Epiſtle by <hi>S. Paul, and not hid elſewhere, or farre fetched,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> expoundeth the <hi>Apoſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But of all authorities of Scripture alleged by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, that which <hi>S. Paul</hi> writeth to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 2.2.15. is in ſhew moſt cleere for them, <hi>Stand faſt, and keepe the traditions which yee haue beene taught, either by word, or by our Epiſtle.</hi> In which words the Apoſtle maketh mention of doctrine not only written, but alſo taught by <hi>expreſſe word of mouth.</hi> Which as we ingenuouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, it being a truth; ſo we ſay withall, that it maketh nothing for our aduerſaries. For although at that time, when the Apoſtle wrote thoſe Epiſtles to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> (<note n="ſ" place="margin">Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. tom. <hi>1.</hi> an. <hi>53.</hi> num. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> which are more ancient then diuers of the writings of the <hi>Euangelists,</hi> and the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles) ſome, yea <hi>many points of doctrine were deliuered in the Church by word of mouth;</hi> yet this is not againſt vs, which haue thoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> which <hi>the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> had not then: In all which now written, <hi>we affirme to be comprehended all things which concerne faith and good manners, and whatſoeuer is needfull to be beleeued: ſo, as that it is either expreſly written, or by neceſſarie conſequence may ſoundly be deduced and concluded out of the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For concerning the old Law, <hi>Moſes</hi> giueth this charge in the perſon of God: <hi>You ſhall put nothing thereto, neither take ought therefrom, Deut.</hi> 4 2. And of the Goſpell, <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that though himſelfe, or an Angell from heauen preach otherwiſe then that which he had preached to the Galatians, let him be accurſed,</hi> 1.8.9. The like is <hi>S. Iohns</hi> teſtimonie of the things recorded in his Goſpell: <hi>Theſe things are written
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19429:24"/> that yee might beleeue, that Ieſus is the Chriſt, the ſonne of God, and that in beleeuing, yee might haue life through his name, c.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 31. Vpon which words, <hi>Hugo</hi> the Cardinall hath this remarkable note: <hi>Specialiter intentio huius libri, generaliter verò totius Scripturae finis, his verbis declaratur: By theſe words, the ſcope of this Gospell in ſpeciall is ſhewed; but in a generalitie, the end of the whole Scripture is declared.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording heerein with <hi>S. Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16.17. <hi>The whole Scripture is giuen by inspiration of God, and is profitable to teach, to improoue, to correct, and to inſtruct in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be abſolute, being made perfect vnto all good workes.</hi> So the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> witneſſeth of <hi>the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the Lord,</hi> that <hi>it giueth wiſdome to the ſimple. Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Euen that wiſdome which is able to make vs wiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſaluation, through the faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim. c.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 15. Therefore when one demanded of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>what he might doe to inherit eternall life;</hi> hee referred him to the Scripture for his direction, <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.25.26. As <hi>Abraham</hi> ſent the rich Gluttons brethren to ſchoole to <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and the Prophets,</hi> that he might <hi>auoid the torment of hell fire, Luc.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 28.29.</p>
            <p>If then the Scriptures are ſo perfect, that wee muſt adde nothing to them, nor take ought from them; if no other Goſpell muſt bee preached, vnder paine of Gods curſe; if by the writings of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Euangeliſts</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> we beleeue that Ieſus is the Chriſt, the ſonne of God, and by faith in his name, obtaine eternall life; if they make the man of God abſolute, and giue wiſdome to the ſimple, that wiſdome which maketh wiſe vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if they direct vs to eternall life, and keepe vs from the torments of hell fire; it is as cleere as the Sunne-light at noone day, that they containe <hi>all things neceſſarie for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> not contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their ſufficiencie, doe the very ſame, for which our Sauiour <hi>rebuked the Scribes and Phariſeis, Mat.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>tranſgreſſe the Commandements of God by their Traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19429:24"/>
            <p>Now if beſide the voice of God ſpeaking in his holy word, any heere preſent, require further the witneſſe of man, and deſire to know the minde and opinion of the ancient Fathers; although where God ſpeaketh, it may well become man to be ſilent, yet that it may appeare, that we teach the ſame doctrine with the old Greeke and Latine Church, it ſhall not be amiſſe, the rather for the ſtopping of the mouthes of our aduerſaries, who are alwaies brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Fathers (of whom they are the degenerate children) to obſerue their iudgement in this point.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore,<note n="t" place="margin">Quod per Dei voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Scripturis nobis tradide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; columna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fidei noſtrae futurum. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the Gospell which the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts deliuered in the Scriptures, is the foundation and pillar of our faith.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Ad puteos Scripturarum, ad aquas Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti &amp; haurire ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per, ac ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um vas ref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rre domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. hom. <hi>10.</hi> in Geneſ.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> inſtructeth vs to haue <hi>daily recourſe to the Wels of the holy Scripture, the waters of Gods holy Spirit; and to draw from thence, and to carry home our veſſels full, like holy Rebecca.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. li. <hi>1.</hi> hiſtor. Eccleſ. ca. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, in his ſpeech to the Biſhops aſſembled in the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> hath this worthy ſaying: <hi>The bookes of the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts and Apoſtles, together with the Oracles of the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, doe plainly teach vs the things which we are to know con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning God. Athanaſius</hi> in his Oration againſt Idols, the<note n="z" place="margin">Piae Religionis &amp; veritatis de vniuerſo ratio cognitioque, per Chriſti doctrinam, ſole cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ſeſe demonſtrat.</note> very firſt words thereof, <hi>The reaſon and knowledge of godly Religion and truth, doth demonſtrate it ſelfe, more cleerely then the Sunne, by the doctrine of Chriſt.</hi> And immediately after,<note n="a" place="margin">Sufficiunt quidem per ſe, tum ſacrae &amp; diuinitus inſpiratae Scripturae, ad veritatis indicationem.</note> 
               <hi>The holy and inſpired Scriptures from aboue, ſuffice by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for the finding out of the truth.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>pag.</hi> 394.</note> 
               <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, that <hi>it is a manifest falling from the faith, and crime of arrogancie, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reiect any thing which is written, or to adde any thing which is not written.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Omnia clara ſunt &amp; plana ex Scripturu diuinu: quaecunque neceſſaria ſunt, manifeſta ſunt, homil. <hi>3.</hi> in <hi>2.</hi> Theſſal.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> yet more directly to the point: <hi>All things are cleere and plaine out of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19429:25"/> whatſoeuer things are neceſſarie, are manifeſt.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Non omnia quae D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minus fecit, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcripta ſunt: ſed quae ſcribentes, tam ad mores quam ad dogmata putarunt ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: vt recta fide, &amp; oper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; virtule ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lantes, ad regnum, &amp;c. l. <hi>12.</hi> in Iob. c. <hi>68</hi>
               </note> So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>S. Cyril: All things are not written, which our Lord did; but tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e things which the Euangeliſts the Writers did thinke to ſuffice, both for manners of life, and precepts of faith: that ſhining with a right faith, and good workes, and vertue, wee might come to the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. De Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxa fide, li. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Damaſcene</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that <hi>he receiueth, and acknowledgeth, and reuerenceth, all things which are deliuered in the Law and the Prophets, the Apoſtles and the Euangeliſts, ſeeking after nothing beyond theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yee haue heard by theſe, what the opinion is of the <hi>Greeke Fathers,</hi> concerning <hi>the ſufficiencie of the Scriptures, without the ſupplie of traditions:</hi> With whom in like ſort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre the Fathers of the Latine Church.<note n="f" place="margin">Scripturae plenitudinem adoro. aduerſ. Hermoginem.</note> 
               <hi>I adore</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian) the fulneſſe of the Scriptures.</hi> And immediately after:<note n="g" place="margin">Scriptum eſſe doceat Hermogenis officina, aut t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meat Vae illud, adijcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus aut detrahentibus deſtinatum. ib.</note> 
               <hi>Let Hermogines his ſhop teach, that it is written; or let him feare that</hi> Woe <hi>appointed for them which adde or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract any thing from the Scriptures.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Vnde eſt iſta traditio? vtrumne de dominica &amp; Euangelica authoritate deſcendens; an de Apoſtolorum mandatis atque Epiſtolis veniens? Ea enim facienda eſſe, quae ſcripta ſunt, Deus teſtatur, &amp;c. ad Pompeium contra Epiſtolam Stephani.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> diſtinguiſhing of Traditions, maketh this demand: <hi>Whence is it?</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Doth it deſcend from the authoritie of our Lord, or his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts; or commeth it from the commandement of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and their Epiſtles? For God witneſſeth, that thoſe things are to be done, which are written.</hi> And immediately after, he inferreth this concluſion:<note n="i" place="margin">Si ergo aut in Euangelio praecipitur, aut in Apoſtolorum epiſtolis aut actibus continetur, &amp;c. obſeruetur etiam &amp; haec ſancta traditio. ib.</note> 
               <hi>If therefore it be commanded in the Gospell, or comprehended in the Epiſtles or Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, &amp;c. let this holy tradition bee kept and obſerued alſo.</hi> But on the other ſide, it hath no ground in the word of God. Then marke what<note n="k" place="margin">Alia quae abſque authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, &amp; teſtimonijs Scripturarum, quaſi traditione Apoſtolica ſponte reperiunt, atque con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingunt haeretici; percutis gladius Des. Jn ca. <hi>1.</hi> Aggei.</note> 
               <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſaith: <hi>Other things, which Heretikes doe finde of their owne accord, without the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and witneſſe of the Scriptures, as though they were</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19429:25"/> by Apoſtolical tradition, the ſword of God (which is his holy word. Epheſ. 6.17.) cutteth off. But of all the ancient Fathers, the iudgement of Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your obſeruation, as being moſt ſound, and directly to the purpoſe, who writing againſt<note n="l" place="margin">Siue de Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto ſiue de eius eccleſia, ſiue de quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia re, quae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet ad fidem vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> noſtram non dicam nos nequa qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com parandi ei, qui dixit, licet ſi nos, ſed omnino quod ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utus adiecit, ſi an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus de caela vobis annuncia uerit preterqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus legalibus et euangelic is accepiſtis, ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra literas Petilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Petilian</hi> the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>natiſt, denounceth this ſentence, as it were with the ſpirit of the Apoſtle. Whether of Chriſt, or of his church, or of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing which appertaineth to faith, and to our life and conuerſation, I ſay not wee, who are by no meanes to bee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with him, who ſaid, but <hi>though that we</hi> &amp;c. Gal. c 1. v. 8. but that which the Apoſtle added, <hi>if an Angell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen preach vnto you otherwiſe beſides that which yee haue receiued in the Scriptures of the law and the Goſpel, let him be accurſed.</hi> And in his Booke <hi>de Doctrina Chriſtiana li.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9. In<note n="m" place="margin">In jis quae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perte in ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris poſita ſunt inueniuntur illa omnia, quae con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moreſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di ſpem ſcilicet at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> charitatem. <hi>Act. 26.28.</hi>
               </note> thoſe things which are ſet down plainely in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, all thoſe things are to bee found, which concerne Faith, and the manners of a mans life, namely hope and charitie.</p>
            <p>Theſe teſtimonies of the ancient Fathers, are plaine and euident, and taken out of ſuch their writings, as are on all parts confeſſed to bee their owne, and not counterfeited, ſuch as our aduerſaries vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preſſe vs with in their daily diſputes; and they are ſo forcible euen with them, that with <hi>Agrippa</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come almoſt Chriſtians: and ſubſcribe to as much in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as we teach of the ſufficiencie of the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Quae fidei ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritates abſolute et ſimpliciter ab omnibus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſario cognoſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae et credendae ſunt, vt et fide, et ſpe, et chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ad beatitu dinem con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere valeant. eas non diffite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icue fere, in ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ipſis doceri vt Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inus etiam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lauit Analy. fidei cathol. l <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Valentia,</hi> a Ieſuite of great note amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, acknowledgeth, that what verities of faith are abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſimplie neceſſarie to bee knowne and beleeued of all men, that they may bee able to come to euerlaſting bliſſe by faith, hope, and charitie, thoſe (ſaith he) wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie not to be taught in the Scriptures themſelues, <hi>perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuè ferè,</hi> almoſt and in a manner plainly, as Saint <hi>Auguſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine</hi> hath alſo noted. But this <hi>fere</hi> almoſt, which the Ieſuite inſerteth, is like to that wicked gloſſe, which corrupteth S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his text. Of the two, Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19429:26"/> more ingenuouſlie, acknowledging<note n="o" place="margin">Dico illa om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſcripta eſſe quae ſunt omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus neceſſaria de verb. dei. l. <hi>4</hi> ca <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> that all thoſe things (without any <hi>fere</hi> almoſte) are written of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which are neceſſarie and needefull for all mens knowledge. And<note n="p" place="margin">Non infici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amur precipua illa fidei capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, quae omni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis cognitu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut ad ſalutem ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsaria, perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>è ſatis eſſe Apoſtolicis ſcriptis compre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſa. c. de ſcriptura. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coſter</hi> the Ieſuite in his Enchiridion: we deny not (ſaith he) that thoſe chief heads of faith which are needefull to bee knowne of all Chriſtians for their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, are contained plainely enough in the writings of the Apoſtles. To whome I might adde a cloud of witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their own writers, both moderne and more ancient, iuſtifying againſt themſelues, what wee teach of the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie of the holy Scriptures: but I muſt omit them for breuities ſake.</p>
            <p>What then meane thoſe reproachfull ſpeeches of the Papiſts, concerning the inſufficiencie, obſcuritie, vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, and inualiditie of the Scriptures, as I haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Wherefore is it, that they ſeale them vp in an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne tongue, that the vnlearned may not vnderſtand them?<note n="q" place="margin">Jndex libror. prohibitorum regul. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Why<note n="r" place="margin">Nauar Enchi rid. <hi>c. 11.</hi> nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>26</hi>
               </note> prohibit they the common people from reading them? why is it accounted a mortall ſin amongſt them for a lay perſon to diſpute of matters of Faith?<note n="ſ" place="margin">De expreſſo dei verbo.</note> why doth <hi>Hoſſius</hi> auouch, that it is fitter for women to meddle with their diſtaffe then with Gods word? why doth<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>De verbo dei</hi> l. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> 
               <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſo greeuouſlie complain, that the tranſlated bibles are in the hands of all artificers, not onely men but Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men? but that by theſe woluiſh voices of theirs, you ſhold know them to bee the generation of thoſe falſe Prophets and ancient Heretikes, whome<note n="u" place="margin">De reſurrec. carnis.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian,</hi> for contempt and ſhunning of the Scriptures, calleth <hi>Lucifugas Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum</hi> ſuch as flie the cleere light of the holy Scriptures, and the wicked broode of<note n="x" place="margin">Melius eſta ſcripturarum lectione homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nines arcere quam ab Jdolothytorum cibis. Ciril. contra. Iul. l. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iulian</hi> that Apoſtata, who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected this as a crime and imputation to the Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they kept not men from reading of the Scriptures: as the Papiſts at their pleaſures now adaies, tearme vs<note n="z" place="margin">Chambers in his epiſt to the Reader.</note> Scripturiſts, and<note n="a" place="margin">Jdem in his epiſt. to the King.</note> worthy Scripturians.</p>
            <p>The voice of the ſhepheard and Biſhop of our ſoules, is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19429:26"/> after another note, willing vs to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39. And ſo ſaith the Prophet <hi>Eſay, to the Law, and to the teſtimonie,</hi> 8.20. And <hi>S. Peter commendeth ſuch as take heed to the words of the Prophets, as vnto a light that ſhineth in a darke place,</hi> 2. c. 1. v. 19. By which the noble <hi>Iewes</hi> of <hi>Berea,</hi> made triall of <hi>S. Pauls</hi> doctrine, <hi>ſearching the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures daily, whether thoſe things were ſo, Act.</hi> 17.11. And in <hi>Theodorets</hi> time,<note place="margin">He flouriſhed about the yeere 433. <hi>Genebrard.</hi>
               </note> it was ſo farre from being a ſinne or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, to be conuerſant and skilfull in the Scriptures, or that any were forbid the reading of them, that contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,<note n="b" place="margin">Sutores, ſabri ferrarij, lanifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, foeminae omnes, agrico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae, foſſores, bubulci, &amp;c. de curandis Graecorum aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctibus, l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Artificers, and thoſe of the meaner ſort, as Smiths, Weauers, Deechers, Heards-men, Coblers, with women of all ſorts, Miſtreſſes and maid-ſeruants, did know and vnderſtand them, and<note n="c" place="margin">De diuina trinitate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creatione de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certantes, ib.</note> diſpute of high points and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their ſaluation.</p>
            <p>And therfore to conclude this point with<note n="d" place="margin">Hom. <hi>9.</hi> in Colloſſen.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> his exhortation, <hi>Audite obſecro ſeculares omnes, &amp;c. Heare (I beſeech you) ye of the Laitie of all ſorts; Comparate vobis Biblia animae pharmaca, &amp;c. If as yet ye haue not, then get you the Bible, which is the very phyſicke of your ſoules, in which you may finde a cure for euery diſeaſe.</hi> As you are Chriſt his ſheepe, ſo heare ye the voice of Chriſt, ſpeaking vnto you in the holy Scriptures; therefore<note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt. de doctrina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana. li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> vt ſcriptura pervarias Jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprcium lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guas lon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téque diffuſa innoteſoeret Gentibus ad ſalutem, &amp;c.</note> tranſlated into diuers tongues and languages, that they might be read and made knowen to men, for their ſaluation. Suffer not your ſelues to be robbed of theſe waters of comfort; neither digge vnto your ſelues the broken pits of vnwritten verities, which can hold no waters: and take this of<note n="f" place="margin">Hom. <hi>9.</hi> in Col.</note> 
               <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> as a moſt grounded truth, that <hi>the cauſe of all euill and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe is, quia Scripturae ignorantur; becauſe men are ignorant in the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of the firſt inſtance, of the <hi>ſufficiencie of the Scriptures, without traditions;</hi> whereby the <hi>Popiſh Doctors</hi> are conuinced to be the <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> of which our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our forewarned vs, in theſe words: <hi>Beware of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19429:27"/>
            <p>The ſecond inſtance which I propoſed, as the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to trie the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> by, is the worſhipping of other gods in ſtead of the true and liuing God, which is God almighty, bleſſed for euermore.</p>
            <p>For ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ferus</hi>) deſcribeth to vs the <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Deuteronom. c.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>&amp;c. If there ariſe amongst you a Prophet, or a dreamer of dreames (and giue thee a ſigne or a wonder, and the ſigne or wonder, which he hath told thee, come to paſſe) ſaying, Let vs goe after other gods, which thou haſt not knowen, and let vs ſerue them; thou ſhalt not hearken to the words of the Prophet, or vnto the dreamer of dreames, &amp;c.</hi> From which teſtimonie of <hi>Moſes, Ferus</hi> gathereth this true propoſition, that<note n="g" place="margin">In cap. <hi>7.</hi> Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</note> 
               <hi>whoſoeuer with-draweth vs from God the Creator, to the creature, falſus Propheta eſt, he doubtleſſe is a falſe Prophet, and one of theſe Wolues cloathed vnder the ſheepes weed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by this note, the <hi>Popiſh Doctors</hi> are ſo manifeſtly deſcried, as nothing can be more plaine and euident.</p>
            <p>For theſe haue made vnto themſelues, their god-ſaints, and their god-ſaints reliques, their breaden-god, their Crucifix-god, their Image-gods, of gold, ſiluer, braſſe, wood, ſtone, and I know not what all. They haue made the Saints not only their Mediators and Interceſſors vnto God, but alſo ioine them with God, as their protectors and defenders. So (ſaith<note n="h" place="margin">In his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the king, prefixed before the miracles of our Lady of <hi>Mont-aigne.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chambers) our Engliſh in their battles call vpon S. George, the Scottiſh nation and the Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, vpon S. Andrew, the French vpon S. Denice, the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards vpon S. Iames.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Chambers, ibid.</note> 
               <hi>They flie vnto them in their maladies and diſeaſes, for their particular helpes; as to S. Sebaſtian and S. Roch, to be preſerued from the plague; to S. Hubert for the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of madde dogs, to S. Blaſius for the paine and ſwelling of the throat,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="k" place="margin">Dicat vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Deus aliquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do infir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ior fuerit, quam v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> potuerit prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe eis, &amp;c verum non dignatus eſt, inquit, hoc facere: at hoc eſſet crimen ſuperbiae. Cyril. contra Julian. li. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> As though God were not all-ſufficient and able of himſelfe, or at leaſt wiſe not willing to defend and ſuccour vs. <hi>They build and dedicate Temples and Altars in their honour, appoint their feſtiuall daies, and ſet formes of ſeruice; they burne incenſe before their Reliques and Images,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19429:27"/> light Tapers before them, goe on pilgrimage vnto them; they garni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h them with all manner offerings, of gold, ſiluer, iewels, and whatſoeuer elſe may ſerue to make them ſeeme glorious in the eies of fooliſh and ſuperſtitious men; they reuerence them with cap and knee, fall downe proſtrate before them, make their praiers vnto them before their Images, yea to the Images them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi> Thus, although their foreheads are not yet growen ſo whoriſh and impudent, as to call them in plaine termes, <hi>gods;</hi> yet in giuing to them that<note n="l" place="margin">Sacra, ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotia, templu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, altaria, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, dies feſti, &amp; quicquid aliud ad eam ſeruitutem pertinet, quae Deo debetur, &amp; Graecè pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè latria di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur. Aug. de ciuit. Dei. li. <hi>7.</hi> ca. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>diuine and religious ſeruice and worſhip, which is proper to God only, they make them Gods,</hi> ſetting them vp in their Churches to bee adored and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</p>
            <p>Time will not permit, neither is it my intent, to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all theſe ſeuerall ſorts of <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> but to inſiſt onely vpon that which of al others is the moſt blockiſh and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; namely, the worſhipping of <hi>Images:</hi> of which, when I ſhall make it apparant that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtand conuicted, ye may the more eaſily iudge of the reſt of their idolatry.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, this is euinced by the ſecond Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt make thee no grauen image, neither any ſimilitude of things that are in heauen aboue, neither that are in the earth beneath, nor that are in the water vnder the earth. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, neither ſerue them.</hi> In which Commandement, by the firſt clauſe, the making of an Image to repreſent God by, is forbidden; by the ſecond, all manner kinde of religious worſhip, whereby ſuperſtitious men goe about to adore God, at, in, or before an image, any manner of way whatſoeuer. Thus<note n="m" place="margin">Lib. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> writing againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi> giueth the true ſenſe of the Commandement, ſaying that <hi>Religion keepeth Iewes and Chriſtians from worſhipping of God, in Temples, Altars, Images;</hi> becauſe the Law ſaith, <hi>There ſhall be no other gods vnto thee before my face;</hi> and, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor worſhip them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this Commandement<note n="n" place="margin">Prohi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eri imaginem Dei factam ad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primendam perfectam ſimilitudinem formae &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ipſius. Si quis hac ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Deum pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere tentaret, is verum ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum conſtitu e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. De ima. Sanctor. l. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, <hi>It might bee
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19429:28"/> anſwered in a word, that it forbiddeth the making of Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, thereby to expreſſe his nature; which whoſoeuer ſhould attempt; ſhould erect a true idol,</hi> and ſo be guilty of the breach of this Commandement.</p>
            <p>But this the <hi>Gentiles</hi> knew, eſpecially the wiſer ſort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, <hi>Hermes, Zenophon, Euripides, Plato,</hi> as the ancient Fathers of the Church,<note n="o" place="margin">In protrepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad Gentes.</note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Li.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Arnobius</hi> and<note n="q" place="margin">Li. <hi>1.</hi> contra Iulian.</note> 
               <hi>Cyril</hi> record; namely, that <hi>God in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was incomprehenſible, and that it was impoſſible, incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reum corpore ſignificare, to ſignifie and repreſent him in a body, who himſelfe had none.</hi> And therefore they made not their Images, by them to expreſſe their diuine nature; but only ſome effects of it; to which they ſuted their images, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God and his vertues reſpectiuely in them, and not the images themſelues; as<note n="r" place="margin">In <hi>3.</hi> Aquin. quaeſ. <hi>25.</hi> ar. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Caietane,</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">In c. <hi>17.</hi> Actor.</note> 
               <hi>Ferus,</hi> with others of their owne, obſerue. So that if by this anſwer, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> can ſalue themſelues from breach of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in like manner may doe as much; who yet by the iudgement of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> are condemned of Idolatrie, <hi>becauſe they turned the glory of the incorruptible God, to the ſimilitude of the image of a corruptible man, and of birds, and of foure-footed beaſts, and of creeping things. Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>This the Cardinall happily vnderſtanding very well, leaueth his firſt anſwer, and flieth to a ſecond; vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Commandement to forbid the making and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of<note n="t" place="margin">De quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris, quae ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur pro dijs. Bell. de imag. Sanct. li. <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> ſuch Images, which are reputed and taken for gods.</p>
            <p>But this was already forbidden in the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that this anſwer of theirs confoundeth the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, making<note n="u" place="margin">Oporte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, illud non eſſe preceptum diſtinctum à primo, vt reuera dicunt Catechiſmi omnes Latini. Bell. de imag. Sanct. li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> one of two, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe in their Primars and Catechiſmes, that ſo men may not take notice of their idolatrie, when the Commandement is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner as it were razed out.</p>
            <p>But the Commandements are diſtinct: the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning all <hi>falſe gods, Thou ſhalt haue no other Gods before
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19429:28"/> me Exod.</hi> 20.3. The ſecond all <hi>falſe worſhip,</hi> either in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Idols, <hi>by them to repreſent God, or in worſhipping them with any maner of Religious ſeruice. Thou ſhalt make theen grauen Image, &amp;c. thou ſhalt not bow down to them, nor Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. Exod.</hi> 20. v. 4.5. For as God and his Worſhip are two diſtinct thinges, ſo the commandement concerning them, are two different precepts.</p>
            <p>Thus the Iewes (who were moſt accurate in calculating the lawe, and euerie member and part thereof, vnderſtood them to bee diſtinct, as appeareth out of<note n="x" place="margin">Antiquita. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ioſephus</hi> and<note n="y" place="margin">Decalogo.</note> 
               <hi>Philo:</hi> as alſo doe<note n="z" place="margin">In Synopſi.</note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">Jn Exod. ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>8.</hi> haec omnia ſimul nonnulli putant vnum eſſe mandatum quod ſi ita pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur, non com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plebitur decem nume rus man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorum, et vbi iam erit deca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>logi verita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? ib. <hi>Exod. 32.4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Origen; Origen</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging, that ſome tooke them but for one, but (ſaith he) if we doe ſo, the number of the ten commandements will not bee complete, and what then ſhall become of the truth of the decalog?</p>
            <p>Furthermore it is worthy the enquiry, who theſe were, ſo ſottiſh, that tooke images made by the worke of mans hands, for Gods, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith? Surely they were not the Iewes, who worſhipping the Golden Calfe, did not ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as once imagin, that it was God, but by it, did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; in it worſhip the true God <hi>Iehouah,</hi> which brought them out of the Land of Aegipt. Nor the Gentiles: for they as<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Dion, Chryſoſtome,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sermon.</hi> 38</note> 
               <hi>Tirius Maximus</hi> declare, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that in their Images made of Golde, ſiluer, braſſe, Iuorie, &amp;c. They did worſhip <hi>ſummum, primum, maximum deum, the cheefeſt, firſt, and greatest God; the Creator and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of all things.</hi> As for the Chriſtians, <hi>Origen</hi> acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them, as you haue alreadie heard. The Papiſts onely remaine; who heerein, eſpecially the ignorant ſort, are more blockiſh then the Gentiles; reputing the verie ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of wood and ſtone (whome they adore) for God and his Saints</p>
            <p>Thus<note n="c" place="margin">De Jnuentor rerum. l. <hi>6.</hi> ca. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Polydore Virgill</hi> one of their owne, and therefore more like to couer their nakednes, then to lay open their ſhame, more then truth, vrged, reporteth of them, that they were<note n="d" place="margin">Eo inſanie deuentum eſt. &amp;c. Ib.</note> come to that height of madnes, that they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19429:29"/> Images made of wood, ſtone, braſſe, or painted vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the walles, and ſet foorth in diuers culloms;<note n="e" place="margin">Non vi figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, ſed perin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de quaſi ipſae ſenſum alique<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habeant, et iis magis fident quam Chriſto. ib.</note> 
               <hi>non vt figuras,</hi> not as figures or ſhapes, but as if they had ſome ſenſe in them; yea (ſaith he) they put more truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in them, then in Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Hee taxeth other their follies in their offerings and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages vnto them: but beeing too lauiſh of his tongue, the Popiſh<note n="f" place="margin">Index expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator. Belgic. in Polydor.</note> cenſors haue taught him to bee more ſilent heereafter, and not to publiſh ſo vnnaturallie the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fornications of his Mother the holy Church, razing &amp; expunging out of him what I haue obſerued, and much more.</p>
            <p>Thus notwithſtanding, whatſoeuer hath beene hitherto anſwered to the contrarie, the worſhip of Images, vſed in the Church of Rome, is Idolatrie, and condemned by the ſecond commandement,<note place="margin">2. King. 18.4 5</note> and therefore by no meanes, nor in any conſideration whatſoeuer, lawfull.</p>
            <p>Heereunto may bee added the example of that godly King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> who when the people of <hi>Iudah</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Brazen Serpent,<note place="margin">Numb. 21.8.</note> and burnt incenſe vnto it, brake it in peeces, though before time it had beene erected at the commandement of God himſelfe: leauing therby an example to <hi>Chriſtian magiſtrates,</hi> what is to bee done with Images, erected onely by the will-worſhip and curioſitie of ſuperſtitious men, when religious ſeruice is done vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reuel 19.10.</note>For if the Angell, when Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> fel downe to worſhip before his feete, corrected him, and forbad him, ſaying, <hi>See thou doe it not;</hi> adding not onely a reaſon thereof, for <hi>I am thy fellow Seruant;</hi> but alſo inſtructing him in the true ſeruice,<note place="margin">Act. 10. ve. 25.26.</note> 
               <hi>worſhip thou God.</hi> And if Saint <hi>Peter</hi> when <hi>Cornelius</hi> fell down at his feete, and worſhipped him, tooke him vp, ſaying: <hi>ſtand vp, for euen my ſelfe am a man:</hi> what may wee imagin they would haue ſaide, if they had found any ſo blockiſhlie and ſuperſtitiouſly addicted, as to haue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped their Images, which the Papiſts will not, (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19429:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> make fellow Seruants with Gods Saints,<note place="margin">Eſa. 44.10, 19</note> as not bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo good as mortal men; but ſuch as the holy Prophets deſcribe them, <hi>abhominations and profitable for nothing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 10.8. Habac. 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>The doctrine of vanitie, and teachers of lies:</hi> then which, the Frog and Mouſe, the Moule and the Batre, and euerie creeping thing is better, becauſe as<note n="g" place="margin">Jn protreptic.</note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drinus</hi> ſaith, theſe haue life and ſenſe; but images haue none; as the Pſalmiſt deſcribeth them, <hi>they haue eyes and ſee not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">115. <hi>v.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>eares and heare not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſt of all, will the Papiſts haue vs worſhip Images? let them produce ſome example out of holy Scripture for this practiſe; and wee will follow it: let them alleage ſome precept of God, ſome exhortation of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles or Prophets, for our warrant, and we obey: which if they cannot doe (as hitherto they haue not, neither can doe, themſelues with one voice confeſſing that this point of Doctrine is grounded vppon tradition wherein what force there is hath beene declared:) then wee ſaie with Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>De bono viduitatis, c.</hi> 1 or who ſoeuer he were that compiled that worke, <hi>Sancta ſcriptura doctrinae noſtrae regulum figit, ne audeamus ſapere plus quam oportet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.3.</note> the holy Scripture pitcheth the rule of our Doctrine in ſuch ſort, that wee preſume not to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand aboue that which is meete to vnderſtand, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth, not daring in matters of Religion and Gods ſeruice, to turne aſide <hi>from the holy Scripture ſo much as one ſtep, either to the right hand or to the left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much leſſe then to the worſhipping of Images, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid by God himſelf, &amp; condemned by all the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or the Church, when ſhe was moſte pure and in her prime?<note n="h" place="margin">l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cont. Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum. impoſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le eſt vt quideu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> norit, ſupplex fiat ſtatuis.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith that it cannot be, that a man ſhould know God, and worſhip Images. And<note n="i" place="margin">Non eſt dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quin reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio nulla ſit, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum eſt. l. <hi>2</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> putteth it out of al doubt, <hi>that there is no Religion where an Image is erected to bee worſhipped.</hi> Therefore<note n="k" place="margin">Nobis nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in mundo quoniam in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus genitis, nihil potest dei re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre imagine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib <hi>6.</hi> Stro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> teacheth, that <hi>men are to learne from the Apoſtle, that they haue no Image in the world, becauſe amongſt the Creatures
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19429:30"/> there is nothing that can reſemble the image of God. S.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Regem ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauit non lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u vt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quia hic g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur, et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> impio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raun illum qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dum in igno. De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eodoſii.</note> 
               <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bro e</hi> yet more directly to the purpoſe, ſpeaking of <hi>Helen,</hi> who by the title found out the Croſſe wheron our Sauiour was crucified: <hi>ſhe worſhipped</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the King not the wood at all, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cauſe this is the error of the Gentiles, and the vanitie of wicked men; but ſhee worſhipped him, who hung on the Tree, that is Chriſt the Lord:</hi> Whereof<note n="m" place="margin">Cultores d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i imaginem ado rare no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. <hi>3.</hi> Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> giueth the reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch as are worſhippers of God, ought not to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe an Image. So likewiſe Saint<note n="n" place="margin">Noui multos eſſe ſepulchro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum et pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum adorato res, quos Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, et quos quotidie ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malos filios cor rigere ſtudet, de moribus ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiae cathol. c. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I knowe (ſaith he) <hi>that there are many Worſhippers of Sepulchers and pictures, &amp;c. whoſe maners the Church condemneth, and which ſhe indeuoureth to correct and amend daily, as being euill Sonnes;</hi> which was the labour and diligence of Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the time of<note n="o" place="margin">Quia eas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorari ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſſes o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ino laudaui mus. Ep. l <hi>9.</hi> Ep. <hi>9</hi> et l. <hi>7.</hi> ep. <hi>109.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, as appeareth by his Epiſtle to <hi>Serenus,</hi> in which hee teacheth expreſlie, that Images are not to bee worſhipped. And this was the current Doctrine of the Church, for the ſpace of 600. yeares after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The greater is the vntruth which Cardinall<note n="p" place="margin">Imagines ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um honorem in eccleſia ſemper habuerunt, de imag. li. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſetteth abroach, affirming that <hi>Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ges haue alwaies had due honor in the Church.</hi> For vntill the ſecond<note n="q" place="margin">which was in the yeare 788. <hi>Center. Magdebur. Cent.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>pa.</hi> 589.</note> 
               <hi>Nicene</hi> councel a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſembled by the ſuperſtitious Empreſſe <hi>Eirene,</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring and worſhipping of images was neuer publikelie eſtabliſhed: and then beeing authorized, it was eft-ſoones diſanulled by a councell held at<note n="r" place="margin">Anno. <hi>794.</hi> cent. Magd. ib. pa. <hi>626.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k-ford,</hi> vnder <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, which defined out of Gods word, that the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of images was vnlawful; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing againſt that of <hi>Neece,</hi> that it was <hi>Pſeudo ſynodus</hi> a falſe Synod or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and therefore no credit to bee giuen to it. Since which time, many haue riſen amongſt themſelues, in the verie height of Poperie, which haue gaineſaid it.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Spiritus. S. aggredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur reprobare idololatras, qui colunt imagines &amp; artificiales figuras. lectio. <hi>158</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Holcot</hi> in his Lectures vpon the book of Wiſdome ſaith, <hi>that the ſpirit of God reprooueth Idolaters, that worſhip ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and artificiall figures:</hi> condemning the determination
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19429:30"/> of <hi>Thomas</hi> 3. <hi>ſentent. diſtinct.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Idem honor debetur ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gini, &amp; illi cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ius eſt imago. ib.</note> 4 <hi>that the ſame honour is due to the image, which is due to him whoſe image it is.</hi> And ſo<note n="u" place="margin">Imagines non adoramus nec deos appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus, necſoem ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ineis porimus, quia hoc eſſ t idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae Rational li. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus, We do</hi> not, ſaith hee, <hi>adore images, nor call them Gods nor put our hope in them, becauſe this were to commit Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ad adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum et colen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum prohiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur imagines, fieri. in Expoſit <hi>1.</hi> precepti</note> 
               <hi>Gerſon</hi> in like manner, <hi>Images are forbidden to bee made to be adored and worſhipped either inwardly by the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the minde, or outwardly in the body, by bowing before them, or bending the knee vnto them.</hi> Who further aduiſeth<note n="y" place="margin">Iudicate ſi tantae imaginu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; picturarum in eccleſiis vari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etas expediat &amp; an populos ſimplices non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunquam ad idololatriam peruertat De clara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> defectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iror Eccleſiaſtic. dec <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> the Clergie of his times, to conſider <hi>whether ſuch varietie of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages &amp; pictures in the church, be profitable or not, &amp; whether they do not ſometime peruert the ſimple people to Idolatry.</hi> That which <hi>Gerſon</hi> propoſeth by way of queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note n="z" place="margin">Vt fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lius, ita tutius quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eſt, omnes imagines ê templis ſummouere, quam impetrare, vt nec modus praetereatur, nec admiſceatur ſuperstitio Jn ſymbolo.</note> 
               <hi>Eraſ.</hi> a man of exquiſite learning, after diligent enquirie made, deliuereth in plain words after this maner: that <hi>as it is more eaſiy, ſo it is alſo more ſaf, to remoue al images out of churches, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to obtain, that either a mean be kept in their worſhip, or that ſuperſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not mingled with al.</hi> To theſe J might ad, their biſhops<note n="a" place="margin">Haec non proprie dícuntur, neque ſecundum verita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em, iuxta com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acceptione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vocabulorum, ſcil cet quod imago, vt imago, avt vt excreas officiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imaginis, quod eſt repreſentare Chriſtum aut deum, ſit adoranda adoratione l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tríae. De tultu imaginum</note> 
               <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>harinis,</hi> &amp;<note n="b" place="margin">Nos nihil numinu tribuimus imagini, neque ei diuinos honores domus. De traditionibus pa. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>222</hi> de cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u imag li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pereſius,</hi> both of them denying that Images are to be worſhipped with diuine worſhip: ye, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, howſoeuer he maintaine the Doctrine which now is moſte current in the Church of Rome, <hi>that</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
               <hi>the images of Chriſt and the Crucifix, are to be worſhipped with Latria,</hi> that is, <hi>Diuine Worſhip;</hi> by his diſtinction of <hi>improprie &amp; per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, improperly:</hi> (by which diſtinction,<note n="d" place="margin">Quaelibetres poſſet a dorari per accidens vbi ſupra.</note> euerie thing might be worſhipped with latria and diuine Worſhip, ſaith <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine,</hi> ſo fooliſh is this diſtinction in his iudgement) yet as though his conſcience checked him, he<note n="e" place="margin">Quantumad modum loq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>endi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raeſertim in concione ad populum, non eſt dicendum imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vllas adorari deberelatria, ſed é co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trario, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> debere ſic adorari Deculto, &amp;c. imag. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> thinketh it no ſound kinde of ſpeech, for the preacher to vſe in the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit; and rather the contrarie: that no images are to bee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19429:31"/> worſhipped with diuine worſhip. A wholeſome peece of Doctrine ye may ſuppoſe, which dareth not abide the light; yet heerein hee ſaid not ſo much, as <hi>Durandus</hi> did before him, who acknowledging the poſition of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to bee falſe, <hi>that the ſame reuerence is to bee giuen to the image, that is giuen to the thing ſignified thereby:</hi> yet ſaith he,<note n="f" place="margin">Apud Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicium in exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>min. concil. Tridentin par. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>loquendum vt vulgus, we muſt speake and ſay as the manie doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus yee ſee the Popiſh Doctors, like<note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> the <hi>Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> ſheathing their ſwords euerie man in his neighbours bowels.</p>
            <p>Onely <hi>Gregorie</hi> of <hi>Valentia</hi> more audacious, that I ſay not, more impudent then the reſt, not being able to purge himſelfe and his Church, from this ſinne of Idolatrie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth to prooue that<note n="h" place="margin">Illud co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donon om dem imaginum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerationem eſſe prohibitam de idol. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>all Worſhipping of images is not forbidden, that is, that ſome Idolatrie is lawfull, becauſe</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> writeth. 1.4.3. <hi>It is ſufficient for vs, that we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue ſpent the time paſt of the life, after the luſt of the Gentiles, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tonnes luſts dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kennes in glutronie, drinkings, et illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citis Idoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cultibus, &amp; in vnlawfull worſhipping of Images,</hi> as he readeth after the vulgar, for that which<note n="i" place="margin">Eraſmus, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias Monta</note> others of his own verie learned, <hi>tranſlate, nefarijs Idolorum cultibus: ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable worſhipping of images.</hi> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which words this great Ieſuite<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <p>Neque abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de profecto putaueris. b. Petruminſiau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſe cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem ſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crorum nempe ſacrarum ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum rectum eſſe, cum fideles no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatim, ab illi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tis idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cultibus, deterrere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luit.</p>
                  <p>Quid enim at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatè cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mulachro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum illicitos notare, ſi omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſimu lachrorum cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus licitos eſſe cenſuiſſet. de idol. l. c. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> maketh this collection: that a man may thinke without abſurditie, that Saint <hi>Peter gaue vs to vnderſtand that ſome worſhip of Idols, namely of holy Images, was right, when he wold deterr the faithfull by name, from the vnlawfull worſhipping of Images; for elſe what needed he to haue noted ſo diſtinctly, the vnlawfull worſhipping of Images and Idols; if hee had thought that no kinde of worſhip had beene lawfull?</hi> which manner of reaſoning if it bee ſound, then may ſome ſinnes be ſaid to bee godly, (which is, to ſpeake good of euill, for which there is a woe ſtored vp. Eſa. 5.20.) becauſe Saint <hi>Iude</hi> calleth <hi>ſinners wicked. v.</hi> 15. which he <hi>needed not to haue done ſo diſtinctly; if ſome ſinners were not godly.</hi> And <hi>Shechem,</hi> or any wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fornicator, or adulterer, may as wel maintain
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19429:31"/> his filthie luſt; becauſe it is ſaid of the defiling of <hi>Dinah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.7.</note> that it was, <hi>res illicita, an vnlawfull thing,</hi> which the ſpirit of God needed not to haue noted ſo diſtinctly, if hee had thought, that no deflowring of virgins had been lawfull. And in that<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi> Acts &amp; Monum. pag. 957. &amp; 1024.</note> great controuerſie which buſied the heads of all the learned, in the famous Vniuerſities of Europe, I meane the cauſe of diuorce betweene <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8. of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorie, and the Lady <hi>Catherin Princeſſe Dowagar,</hi> ſometimes wife to his brother Prince <hi>Arthur;</hi> the Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates on the Ladies part might haue argued ſtrongly out of the Scriptures (after <hi>Valentia</hi> his manner) for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the marriage, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Leuitic.</hi> c. 20. v. 21. <hi>The man that taketh his brothers wife, committeth an vnlawfull thing, rem facit illicitam.</hi> For if ſome marriage of a man with his brothers wife were not lawfull, what needed <hi>Moſes</hi> at the Commandement of God to haue noted ſo diſtinctly, <hi>the vnlawfull marriage of the brothers wife?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ignorant man, ſhall I ſay, or malitiouſly blinde, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knoweth not, or diſſembleth that which boies in the Schooles learne in their firſt rudiments, that <hi>Epithets</hi> are vſed, not ſo much for diſtinction ſake, as by way of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification and exaggeration: and yet, as though the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of diſtinction were only in vſe. So the <hi>Ieſuite</hi> peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the place of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> who vſed the <hi>Epithet</hi> of <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> or <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>abominable idolatrie,</hi> exag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerating the heinouſneſſe of the offenſe, becauſe <hi>idolatrie</hi> is the greateſt and moſt heinous of all ſinnes, as himſelfe<note n="m" place="margin">De Idololat. li. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> elſwhere truly prooueth out of the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Thus by the verdit of Gods word, and teſtimonies of the ancient Fathers, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſtand conuicted of <hi>idolatrie;</hi> thereby ſhewing themſelues to be the off-ſpring of theſe old Heretikes, the<note n="n" place="margin">Euſeb. hiſtor. Eccl. l <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Simonians,</hi> the<note n="o" place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nae. li. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gnoſtiques,</hi> the<note n="p" place="margin">Epiphan hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>27.</hi> &amp; <hi>79.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridians;</hi> and to be thoſe <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> and <hi>rauening Wolues,</hi> clad in <hi>ſheepes-cloathing,</hi> of which our Sauiour heere gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth warning, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets.</hi> And ſo I come to the third inſtance, which is their <hi>Miracles,</hi> alleged com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19429:32"/> as an argument; as for other points of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſo for the worſhipping of Images. The confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the one will be the ouerthrow of the other.</p>
            <p>Now concerning theſe <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> wee haue our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours prediction, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. <hi>There ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſt, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſo that if it were poſſible, they ſhould deceiue the very elect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As then our Sauiour teacheth vs by the parable of the figge-tree,<note place="margin">Matth. 24.32.</note> 
               <hi>when her bough is tender, and it bringeth foorth leaues, wee know that Summer is neere;</hi> ſo likewiſe when wee ſee and heare the ſignes and wonders whereby the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> laboureth to commend vnto vs many her nouell and ſuperſtitious doctrines, and amongſt them the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images,</hi> wee may by them take perfect notice of the comming of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> which the holy Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told ſhould be,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>by the working of Satan, with all powers, and ſignes, and lying wonders, and in all deceiueableneſſe of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe:</hi> which in theſe latter ages of the doting world we haue ſeene accompliſhed in the <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Synagogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For amongſt them, their images, for example ſake, haue beene ſeene,<note n="q" place="margin">Concil. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. ſecund. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to ſweat, to weepe, to laugh, to diſtill drops of dew,</hi> with which, diſeaſes haue beene cured, to ſhift them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from place to place, yea<note n="r" place="margin">Preuiarium Rom. in feſto S. Thom A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin.</note> to ſpeake alſo; thereby to conuince the <hi>Prophet Dauid</hi> of falſhood, who ſaith of them, <hi>They haue mouthes, and ſpeake not, Pſalme.</hi> 115. verſe 5.</p>
            <p>The<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Action.</hi> 4.</note> Fathers of the ſecond Nicene Councell are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in this argument, reporting that a woman ſicke of the palſie, praving before the image of <hi>S. Anaſtaſius,</hi> roſe vp whole and ſound. Another poſſeſſed with a foule ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, brought before the ſame Saints image at <hi>Rome,</hi> was ſo cured. And that a man moleſted with the diuell, was by him told, that if he would not haue him ſtruggle and wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with him, he muſt beware that he worſhipped no more the image of the Virgin, bearing Chriſt in her armes, as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19429:32"/> ſhe is vſually painted. Whereupon<note n="ſ" place="margin">Carol. mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus de imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Abbot Theodorus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that a man were better frequent all brodell houſes, then to omit the worſhip of that image.</p>
            <p>Examples of this ſort are infinite, <hi>it being an endleſſe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to recite the only bare names</hi> (as<note n="t" place="margin">In his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the king, prefixed before the miracles of our Lady of <hi>Mont-aigue.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Robert Chambers</hi> a <hi>fugitiue Prieſt</hi> ſaith) <hi>of thoſe who haue laudably,</hi> as he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, <hi>imploted their labours heerein.</hi> And therefore, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others, I commend only to your conſideration that pamphlet tranſlated our of French, by him, into our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue, of the Miracles lately wrought before the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of our Lady of <hi>Mont-aigue,</hi> in the Low Countries, and dedicated not long ſince to the Kings Maieſty. Theſe in his Epiſtle dedicatorie, he auoucheth to <hi>be ſemblable to thoſe diuine operations whereby the Sauiour of the world did manifeſt his godhead to the world. For</hi> (ſaith he, turning his ſpeech to the King) <hi>heere your Grace may behold, how the blinde ſee, the deafe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are, the lame walke, the Diuels are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, the Leapers are cleanſed, and many other painfull, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and desperate maladies are cured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed our Sauiour ſaid little more, when hee would ſhew to <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> his two <hi>Diſciples,</hi> that hee was that Chriſt, foretold by the Prophets, to come into the world, for the redemption of mankinde.<note place="margin">Matt. 11.45.6</note> 
               <hi>Goe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſhew Iohn what things yee haue heard and ſeene; the blinde receiue ſight, and the halt goe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the leapers are cleanſed, and the deafe heare the dead are raiſed vp, and the poore receiue the Goſpell. And bleſſed is he that ſhall not be offended in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greater is the blaſphemie of this Popiſh Prieſt, to aſcribe that to a <hi>wodden image,</hi> which was the handy worke of <hi>Chriſt, God and man, the Sauiour and Redeemer of the world:</hi> yet what he briefly repeateth in his Epiſtle, is to be read at large in the hiſtorie of theſe miracles; in which hee is ſo confident, that he ſaith, <hi>It cannot be imagined that his royall wiſdome would paſſe them ouer, as though his Grace had no apprehenſion of them.</hi> Yet to make his imagination the more ſure and ſtrong, hee gathereth together the reaſons
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19429:33"/> and arguments which his great Maſters allege for proofe of the miracles wrought in the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Epiſtle dedic.</note>And firſt (ſaith he) <hi>where miracles are ſeene to fauour the perſons or things that appertaine to their congregation; who can denie, but that God is well pleaſed with them, and well al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of their rites, faith, and profeſſion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will he know who can denie this? I will not now anſwer him with the authoritie of the ancient Fathers, of whom I ſhall ſpeake heereafter; neither of all the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in Chriſtendome, which happily in his eies are but deformed. His fellow Prieſt,<note n="u" place="margin">In his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Sutt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffe</hi> his appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix, fol. 179.</note> 
               <hi>Matthew Kelliſon,</hi> in effect denieth it, acknowledging that <hi>Simon Magus, Montanus, Maximilla, and the Gnoſtique Heretikes, deceiued many by their illuſions, and that Antichriſt at his comming ſhall ſeduce many moe.</hi> As much doth <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine,</hi> reciting out of <hi>Valerius Maximus,</hi> and <hi>M. Ciero,</hi> miracles wrought by the <hi>Pagans,</hi> as that a <hi>Veſtale Virgin drew water in a ſiue; that a Southſaier cut a whetſtone with a raſor.</hi> Which if<note n="x" place="margin">De notis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſet light by, as though they were, as hee calleth them, <hi>leuia, light, and of ſmall account,</hi> yet thoſe which are recounted by the ſame <hi>Valerius,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Tit. de mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis.</note> 
               <hi>li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 8. may not bee ſo anſwered.</p>
            <p>As namely, where the image of fortune is reported to haue ſaid to the Matrons and Ladies of <hi>Rome, Ritè me Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronae vidiſtis, ritéque coluiſtis: Ladies and Matrons, yee did rightly ſee mee, and as well conſecrate me.</hi> For as vnlikely a Miracle as this is chronicled in their <hi>reformed Roman Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiarie,</hi> of the<note n="z" place="margin">Infeſto S. Thom. Aquin.</note> 
               <hi>Image of the Crucifix;</hi> before which, <hi>Thomas of Aquine</hi> praying, he heard a voice (the<note n="a" place="margin">Antonin. hiſ. par. <hi>3.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. <hi>23.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Crucifix</hi> ſpake it) <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſcripfiſtide me, Thoma: Thomas, thou haſt written well of me.</hi> Which is true, if that bee true which hee wrote, that the<note n="b" place="margin">Tom <hi>3.</hi> quaeſ. <hi>25.</hi> artic. <hi>3.0.</hi>
               </note> image of the Crucifix was to be worſhipped with <hi>latria,</hi> ſuch worſhip as wee giue to God: for thereby hee maketh the Crucifix a God; which is well, I trow, for the Crucifix.</p>
            <p>Will any man thinke, that hath eies in his head, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19429:33"/> both theſe miracles came not out of one ſhop, from one and the ſelfe ſame forge?</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>Valerius</hi> reporteth, that the Chapell of the <hi>Salij</hi> being burned, nothing was found in it<note n="c" place="margin">Praeter lituum Romuli. ib.</note> beſides <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mulus his deuming ſtaffe.</hi> The like is recorded amongſt the miracles wrought by our Lady of <hi>Mont-aigue,</hi> that<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pa.</hi> 278.</note> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Heretikes ranſacking her Chapell, and burning the foormes and ſeats, and other things of wood within it, yet the Chapell tooke no fire, although they laboured to burn it alſo.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe reported by <hi>Valerius Maximus,</hi> what ſhall be ſaid of that which<note n="d" place="margin">Jn his life.</note> 
               <hi>Suetonius</hi> writeth of <hi>Vespaſian,</hi> that he reſtored ſight to a blinde man by ſpitting into his eies, and healed another of a lame leg or thigh, by touching of him with his heele? as alſo of that which <hi>Aelias</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Spartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> recordeth of <hi>Adrian,</hi> that hee reſtored one to ſight, that was borne blinde: of that which <hi>Iulius</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Jb.</note> 
               <hi>Capitolinus</hi> reporteth of <hi>Antoninus,</hi> ſurnamed the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, who by his praiers procured lightning from heauen, to ſet his enemies engines on fire, and rain for his armie, when they fainted with thirſt? of that which<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus</hi> hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to writing of <hi>Hercules</hi> &amp; <hi>Apollonius Tyanaeus,</hi> that they raiſed vp the dead to life. Theſe and ſuch like, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> muſt not blow away with his breath, terming them light; for greater miracles then theſe, are not recorded in the moſte lying and fabulous <hi>legends</hi> of Saint <hi>Franciſco, Saint Dominick, Saint Antonie</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> of <hi>Franciſcus Xauerius</hi> out of the <hi>Indies;</hi> or out of the Low-countries of the Image of our Lady of <hi>Mount-aigue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Chambers</hi> his reaſon bee good, it followeth, <hi>that God was well pleaſed with theſe Pagans, and allowed of their rites, faith and profeſſion, becauſe miracles fauoured their perſons,</hi> and then let the Papiſtes ſee what will become of their Church, which<note n="h" place="margin">Bellar. de no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis Eccleſiae. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> they ſay, <hi>is knowne by her Miracles; when the Pagans miracles are as glorious as theirs,</hi> what diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons can the working of miracles make? They<note n="i" place="margin">Arte daemonis opera diaboli. Bel. vbi ſupra. <hi>And Chamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his</hi> Epiſt.</note> will ſay,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19429:34"/> that theſe miracles and cures wrought by the <hi>Pagans,</hi> were no true miracles, but were done by the aide and aſſiſtance of the Deuill; bee it ſo, and what hindreth, why wee may not anſwer in like maner, (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth) <hi>of the cures wrought at the image of our Lady of Mount-aigu,</hi> if any were wrought, and ſuch like? that<note n="k" place="margin">Diabolus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens, in ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vnius, et al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s tibia, impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chal vſum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum membro, rum, id<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t videre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turſanare, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ſineret noce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Bel. ib,</note> the <hi>Deuill being in the eye of one, in the leg of an other,</hi> and ſo in the reſt, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to haue beene cured, <hi>hindred the vſe of thoſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to the end that our Ladie</hi> (to ſpeake with the Papiſts) <hi>might ſeeme to cure them, when the Deuill did deſiſt and leaue off to hurt and hinder them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But miracles (ſaith <hi>Chambers) are works that ſurpaſſe the power of any creature, and therefore where God vouchſafeth to worke any miracle in the defence or honour of any perſon or any point belonging to any religion or beleefe,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">In his Epiſt.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch a miracle is, as it were, his verie word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, if we take miracles in a ſtrict ſenſe, for ſuch works <hi>as are done against nature, as to ſtay the courſe of the ſun in the firmament, to ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e downe Manna from heauen, &amp;c.</hi> So, the holy <hi>Angels themſelues, as by themſelues, can worke no mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles;</hi> much leſſe the Deuill or any his inſtruments, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt or falſe Prophets whatſoeuer; neither are they ſuch that are wrought before the Image of <hi>Mont-aigu:</hi> but if we will ſpeake as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth, and call that a miracle,<note n="m" place="margin">miraculum voco, quicquid a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> aut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſupra ſpem aut facul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatem miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis apparet. de vtil. credendi c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> which beeing hard or not vſual, <hi>appeareth to be doone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the hope and abilitie of men that wonder at it;</hi> as it is com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monly taken, ſueh miracles the deuils can work, and falſe Prophets and ſorcerers by his aſſiſtances, and not onelye the holy Angels. But theſe are no way to bee compared with the authoritie of Gods word, in as much as <hi>true mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles themſelues, without their dependence &amp; congruitie with the Scriptures,</hi> cannot now adaies giue any credit or authority to any point of Doctrine or Religion. And therefore S.<note n="n" place="margin">Eccleſiam ſuam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moſtr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſi poſſint, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſermonibus &amp;c. no in ſignis et pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fal l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cibus &amp;c. ſed in preſcripto legis, in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaetarum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis &amp;c. hoc eſt in omnibus canonicis ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum libroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> authoritatibus. de vnitat. Eccleſ, c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hauing to deale with the Donatiſts, in the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Church, prouoketh and calleth them from their ſignes and wonders, to the praeſcript of Gods word;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19429:34"/> which is the touch-ſtone of all miracles, as<note n="o" place="margin">In c. <hi>24.</hi> Mat. fol. <hi>542.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Ferus</hi> rightly obſerueth from the teſtimonie of <hi>Moſes</hi> and our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our:</hi> vpon which, hee groundeth this true concluſion: <hi>Doctrina non ex miraculis, ſed miracula ex doctrina probanda ſunt; that doctrine muſt not haue his proofe from miracles, but miracles from the truth of doctrine:</hi> howſoeuer<note n="p" place="margin">In his epiſtle dedicat.</note> 
               <hi>Chambers</hi> moſt vntruly, if not blaſphemouſly, auerreth, that <hi>miracles are more euident proofes of a true Religion, then are the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Jbid.</note>
               <hi>But God</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>being truth it ſelfe, cannot by his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie giue his teſtimonie to any error or falſhood: aend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very goodneſſe it ſelfe, it is impoſſible that hee will permit vs to be ſeduced by any his extraordinarie ſupernaturall operations, &amp;c.</hi> Which as I willingly acknowledge to be true, in the elect; ſo I further adde, that God permitteth Satan and his members ſometime to worke miracles, not to the end that he would thereby giue credit and authoritie to their falſe doctrine and haereſies: but as<note n="r" place="margin">In c. <hi>24.</hi> Matht.</note> 
               <hi>Ferus</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Promp. nor. pars aeſtiual. dominica <hi>24.</hi> poſt Pentecoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Stapleton</hi> his Doctors obſerue, and that truly, <hi>ad probationem bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, excaecationem vero malorum; for the proofe and triall of the good his choſen, and excaecation of the wicked and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate:</hi> According heerein with <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 13.1.2.3. <hi>The Lord your God prooueth you, to know whether yee loue the Lord your God, with all your heart, and with all your ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But miracles haue beene alwaies in the Church, from her firſt infancie, and ſo haue continued from age to age, euen to our times, as</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Li. <hi>4.</hi> de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> obſerueth, which to<note n="u" place="margin">In his Epiſt. dedicatorie.</note> 
               <hi>Chambers</hi> ſeemeth an argument vnanſwerable.</p>
            <p>We anſwer, not as he vainly conceiueth, <hi>that all ſuch hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories are fictions;</hi> neither, <hi>by bare and incredulous denials,</hi> as he would make vs, but we diſtinguiſh the times, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that in the primatiue Church, miracles were truly wrought; the exigence of the times ſo requiring, when the doctrine of the Goſpell was ſtrange, new, and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the naturall man; and, as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>to the Iewes a ſtumbling blocke, and to the Graecians fooliſhneſſe:</hi> which gift
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19429:35"/> continued in the Church vntill <hi>both Iewes and Gentiles were generally gathered to Christ his flocke.</hi> And yet, what ſmall force there was in miracles, euen in thoſe times of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to bring men to the truth, when God with-held the inward operation of his holy Spirit, by the efficacie of the word preached, is manifeſt by ſome vnbeleeuing <hi>Iewes,</hi> who aſcribed the miracles wrought by our Sauiour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Matth. c. 9. v. 34. &amp;c. 12. v. 24.</note> to <hi>the power of Beelzebub the prince of the Diuels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the miracles of the latter ages, wee anſwer with<note n="x" place="margin">De vnitate Eccleſ. c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſtine, Aut non ſunt vera either they are not true,</hi> ſuch as are many the <hi>Legendarie Fables,</hi> and the miracles wrought amongſt the <hi>Indians,</hi> by <hi>Franciſcus Xauerius,</hi> and others of that crew, as the<note n="y" place="margin">Bellar. de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Eccleſ. li. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ieſuites</hi> report: <hi>Aut ſi haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aliqua mira facta ſunt, or ſome of them are true, as Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes and Impoſtors in all ages haue wrought ſome,</hi> and ſtill doe by the aſſiſtance of Satan; and then we are to be the more wary of them, as<note n="z" place="margin">De vnitat. Eccleſ c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> teacheth vs, as beeing wrought by the permiſſion of God, for the triall of his children, and further obdurance of the wicked.</p>
            <p>And that we make no more reckoning of their miracles, they muſt not take it amiſſe at our hands: the wiſer and better learned amongſt them haue taught vs to doe ſo, if wee knew it not before.<note n="a" place="margin">Aliquando fit in Eccleſia maxima de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio populi, in miraculis fictis à ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotibus, &amp;c. Gloſſ. in c. <hi>14.</hi> Daniel.</note> 
               <hi>Lyranus</hi> acknowledgeth, that <hi>the people are ſometimes much deceiued in the Church by mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles made by Prieſts and their conſorts, for worldly gaine.</hi> And for the Writers of the <hi>Legends</hi> of their Saints, which are full fraught with them,<note n="b" place="margin">De vanitate ſcientiarum, ca. <hi>97.</hi> Pietatis loco ducunt, men dacia pro reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi ne fingere De traden diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciplinis, li <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> giueth this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of them, that they doe <hi>miracala fabricare,</hi> and <hi>confingere terribiles fabulas,</hi> make miracles after their owne deuices, and faine terrible fables. <hi>Ludouicus Viues</hi> ſaith, that <hi>they hold it for a point of godlineſſe, to coine lies in defenſe and maintenance of Religion.</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>4.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>greſſ. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Claudius Eſpencaeus,</hi> that <hi>no ſtable is ſo full of dung, as the Legends are of fables;</hi> and that <hi>very fictions are contained in their Porteſſes.</hi> So<note n="d" place="margin">Apparat. ſac. tit. Apochry.</note> 
               <hi>Poſſeuine</hi> the <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> the <hi>Criticke</hi> of our age, confeſſeth, <hi>that many hiſtories of the Saints liues are ſo written, vt haereticis ſubſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19429:35"/> cordatis dubitandi, pijs lachrymandi occaſionem praebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant; that they giue occaſion to Heretikes</hi> (it is the liuery which the Ieſuite beſtoweth vpon vs) <hi>to laugh in their ſleeues; to men of courage and iudgement, to ſuſpect them; to deuout and godly men, occaſion to weepe and lament them.</hi> But of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, their Biſhop <hi>Canus</hi> ſetteth them foorth in their colours. Firſt he ſaith that <hi>the Hiſtoriographers amongst the Gentiles, Laertius, Suetonius, and ſuch like,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Longè incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptius &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrius, &amp;c. Loc. Theolog. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> fol <hi>333</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>wrote the liues of their Philoſophers and Emperors, with much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie and ſinceritie then their Catholikes had wrote the liues of their Martyrs, Virgins, and Confeſſors:</hi> which<note n="f" place="margin">Dolenter hoc dico, potius quàm contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliosè, ib.</note> hee vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not by way of reproach, but <hi>from the very griefe of his heart.</hi> He ſaith further, that <hi>whil'ſt they follow their fond affections too much, they make vs</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Tales diuos quandoque nobis exhibent, quales diui ipſi et ſi poſſent, eſſe tamen noluiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ib.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch Saints ſometimes, as the Saints themſelues, if they might, would by no meanes bee ſuch in very deed. Of which ſort, the examples are ſo many, that they cannot be numbred for multitude.</hi> He addeth further that<note n="h" place="margin">Olent aut quaeſtuoſorum hominum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſturam, aut quod Gelaſius ipſe ait, haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum foetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ib.</note> 
               <hi>they ſauour eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of the impoſture and deceit of couetous men; or, as Pope Gelaſius ſaith, of the vntimely fruit of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">res diuorum praeclare geſtas non ſe putant egregiè expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turos, niſi eas fictis &amp; reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationibus &amp; miraculis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornarint, ib.</note> 
               <hi>who thinke they cannot declare the noble deeds of Saints excellently well, vnleſſe they garniſh them with fained, both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations and miracles.</hi> His cenſure of the golden <hi>Legend</hi> is this, that <hi>a man may oftner read in it miraculorum monſtra, monſtrous miracles, rather then true:</hi> branding the Compiler of it with that marke which<note n="k" place="margin">Sueton in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Neronis.</note> 
               <hi>Licinius Craſſus</hi> ſet firſt vpon <hi>Domitius,</hi> that<note n="l" place="margin">Hanc homo ſcripſit ferreioris, plumbei cordis, animiceriè parum ſeueri &amp; prudentis, Canus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b.</note> 
               <hi>he was a man of an iron face, and a leaden heart, and a minde neither ſeuere nor wiſe.</hi> To Diuines hee giueth this holeſome admonition; <hi>that they doe not forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with perſwade themſelues, that all things are abſolutely perfect,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Quae magni authores ſcripſerint. nam &amp; labuntur aliquando, &amp; indulgent ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum ſuorum voluptati, vulgoque, ib.</note> 
               <hi>which great Authors haue written, becauſe they ſlide ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and follow their owne wits will, and yeeld too much to the common people.</hi> In this ranke he placeth his <hi>Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie,</hi> and our <hi>Venerable Bede;</hi> the one in his dialogue, the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19429:36"/> other in his Engliſh hiſtorie, inſerting ſuch miracles, as were vſually in<note n="n" place="margin">Miracula ſcribunt vulgo iactata &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita, quae huius praeſertim ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi Ariſtarchi incerta eſſe cenſebunt. Ib.</note> euery mans mouth, and commonly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued: which the rigid Cenſors of this age, would iudge and repute for no better then vncertaine. And ſpeaking of <hi>Vincentius</hi> and <hi>Antonine,</hi> he ſaith that<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terque non tam dedit ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, vt res veras certaſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deſcriberet, quam ne nihil omnino praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riret, quod ſcriptum in ſchedulis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſlibet repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riretur. Jb.</note> 
               <hi>they both ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, not ſo much to deſcribe matters true and certaine, as that they might not omit ought that they found written in euery ſcrole and caſt peece of paper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the caſe thus ſtandeth, as the learned <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelues deliuer, not onely with the <hi>Legendaries,</hi> with <hi>Vincentius,</hi> and <hi>Antonine;</hi> but alſo with <hi>S. Bede</hi> and <hi>Pope Gregorie,</hi> yea with holy men and very great; that they haue after this manner ſtuffed the hiſtorie of their Saints, with ſuch prodigious and monſtrous falſe miracles; is it not a wonder to behold this punie Prieſt <hi>Chambers,</hi> after the iudgement and cenſure of ſo many learned reputed amongſt them, ſo boldly to inſult, and beare himſelfe vpon the miracles, collected out of their Chronicles and Legends,<note n="p" place="margin">In his epiſt. dedic.</note> 
               <hi>as though no men were able reaſonably to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this hiſtoricall demonſtration,</hi> gathered before to his hand, by his great<note n="q" place="margin">Bell. de notis Eccl. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Maſter <hi>Bellarmine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet will not this true anſwer of <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> giue him ſatisfaction, <hi>vnleſſe we be able, by ſome ancient and</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In his epiſt. dedic.</note> 
               <hi>authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Chronicles, Records, Doctors, or learned Writers, to note the time when God with-drew his powerable hand from theſe kindes of ſupernaturall workes, or that euer they ſhould end ſo long as his Church ſhould laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere then let <hi>Chambers</hi> heare the record of <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> whom hee calleth (and that worthily) <hi>the renowned and famous Champion of Gods Church; who to ſome deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of curioſitie, why thoſe miracles were not wrought now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, which were done in the times of our Sauiour and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? I might</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>anſwer</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Poſſem dicere neceſſaria fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe priuſquam crederet mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, ad hoc vt crederet mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. De ciuit. Dei, li. <hi>22</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that miracles were needfull before the world beleeued, that ſo by them, the world might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. But hee that ſtill requireth miracles, to make him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium, qui mundo credente, non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit;
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19429:36"/> himſelfe is a great wonder and miracle, who beleeueth not now that the world is brought to faith and beleefe.</hi> Of which aſſertion of his, concerning the ceaſing of miracles, after that the world was brought to the faith of Chriſt,<note n="u" place="margin">Nunc ſigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum petitio tentatio eſt. hom. <hi>23.</hi> in Euangel. Iohan</note> hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth many reaſons in other his Treatiſes. As in his booke <hi>de vera Religione,</hi> c. 25. this amongſt others, <hi>ne animus ſemper viſibilia quaereret, that the minde of man ſhould not ſtill ſeeke after things viſible,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Et eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etudine rigeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret genus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manu, quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitate flagrauit</note> 
               <hi>and mankinde wax cold through the daily vſe of miracles, with the noueltie whereof it burned with zeale at the firſt.</hi> And <hi>de vtilitate credendi, c.</hi> 16. <hi>quia non mouerent niſi mira eſſent, at ſi ſolita eſſent, miranon eſſent: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe miracles would not mooue men, vnleſſe they were wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and wonderfull they would not be, if they were vſuall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> accordeth <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> affirming that the <hi>asking of Miracles now adaies, is a tempting of God.</hi> And to the queſtion that ſome then made, as the Papiſts do now, why are not miracles wrought as in former ages? hee returneth this anſwer,<note n="x" place="margin">Si fidelis es vt oportet, ſi Chriſtum dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis vt diligédus eſt, non indiges ſignis, ſigna e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim incredulis dantur. ib</note> 
               <hi>If thou bee faithfull as thou oughteſt to be, if thou loue Chriſt as thou oughteſt to doe, thou needeſt not ſignes and miracles; for theſe</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are for vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the<note n="y" place="margin">Nunc ſignoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> operatio o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nino laeuata est, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et apud eos inuenitur, qui falſi ſunt Chriſtiani, fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri facta. ho. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> author of the vnperfect worke vpon Saint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> his Goſpel, <hi>the working of ſignes and miracles is now cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and at an end, and it is found to be done rather amongſt them qui falſi Chriſtiani ſunt,</hi> who are falſe Chriſtians: let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts if there be any heere preſent, mark the euidence that this author giueth.</p>
            <p>In theſe ſteps of S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> &amp; <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> treadeth their Pope <hi>Greg.</hi> Miracles (ſaith he)<note n="z" place="margin">Signa neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria in exordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſiae fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. Vt enim ad fidem creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret multitudo credentium, mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raculis fuerat nutrie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da, &amp;c. hom. <hi>29.</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangel.</note> 
               <hi>were needful in the church in the beginning thereof, when faith was to bee nouriſhed by them; as men doe water plants which are newly ſet vntill they haue taken roote;</hi> which being done, the watering ceaſeth; and ſo ſay I doe miracles in the Church. So likewiſe our Engliſh<note n="a" place="margin">Numquid quia ista ſigna non facimus, minime credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? ſed haec neceſſaria in exordio Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae fuerunt. l. <hi>4</hi> in Mar. c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bede,</hi> what ſaith he? <hi>Doe we not beleeue, becauſe wee worke not theſe ſignes and miracles? but theſe were needeful in the beginning of the Church.</hi> And <hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
               <hi>Iſidor Hiſpalenſis: The
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19429:37"/> reaſon why the Church worketh not the ſame miracles which were done in the times of the Apoſtles is,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Quod nunc Eccleſia non ea miracula faciat, quae ſub Apoſtolis faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebat, ca cauſa eſt, quia tunc oportebat mun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam miraculis credere, nunc vero iam cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem, oportet bonis operibus coruſcare, de ſummo bono. l. <hi>1,</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>becauſe the world was then to be brought to faith by miracles; but now beleeuing, it muſt ſhine with good workes.</hi> And againe,<note n="c" place="margin">Iam in fide miracula qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> requirit, vanam gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vt laudetur, quaerit. ib</note> 
               <hi>He that now requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth miracles when faith is planted, ſeeketh after vaine glorie, that hee may be praiſed:</hi> he proceedeth further, &amp; auouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in plaine tearmes, that<note n="d" place="margin">Antequam Antichriſtus appareat, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes ab eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia et ſigna ceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſabunt, vt per hoc ſanctorum clareat patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, et reprobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizabuntur leuitas oſtente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, et perſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tíum audacia ferocior effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur, ib.</note> miracles ſhall ceaſe in the Church before the comming of Antichriſt, whereof he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageth theſe reaſons; that by this the patience of Saints may bee famous; and the leuitie of the reprobat, which are offended, may bee ſhewed; and the boldnes of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors may bee made the more fierce.</p>
            <p>To this graue teſtimony of the ancient Fathers, I will add the witnes of ſome of his owne writers, that the neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtupiditie of this Popiſh Prieſt may be ſeene of all men more apparantly. Amongſt them, <hi>Catharinus</hi> in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the worſhipping of Images, hath this ſaying in the end of his treatiſe,<note n="e" place="margin">Non dico vt inde (a cultu imaginu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) expectent oracula &amp; ſigna, quae rara ſunt, neque curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis conceduntur, nec expediret imperfectus ea dari, perfectis autem minime neceſſe eſt. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Men ſhould not looke for Oracles and Miracles from the worſhip of images, which</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>are rare, and not granted to curious perſons; neither is it expedient that they ſhould bee giuen to men that are imperfect; and as for ſuch as are perfect they neede them not. Stella</hi> ſaith, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Miracula potius nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>num nobis offerrent, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commoda. Puer enim quando ambulare inci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pit, adiunatur vehiculo, at ſi homo adultus &amp;c. in Luc. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>miracles now a daies, would rather hurt then profit vs:</hi> as props which are needefull for Children to learne to goe by, are a hindrance vnto them, when they are growne to mans e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; ſo (ſaith hee) if Miracles were wrought now adaies, men would be offended by them, and ſay that our Faith were not as yet wel grounded: beware therefore, leſt it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them to demand a ſigne at Gods hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>ſatis ſint tibi ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vetera,</hi> let the old ſignes &amp; miracles ſuffice, and do not now ſeeke after new. As much ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">Promiſit Christus vt diſcipuli daemonia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ijcerent quam promiſſionem, nullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his diebus effectum ſortiri dilucide cernimus, &amp;c nec tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inanis illa promiſſio fuit, quam nolùit efficaciam habere perpetuam, ſed pro tempore naſcentis et adoleſcentis Eccleſiae. De captiuit. Babilonica adu. Luther. c. <hi>10.</hi> par. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fiſher,</hi> ſometimes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19429:37"/> biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> Chriſt promiſed that his diſciples ſhold caſt out deuils, which promiſe we ſee to take no effect now adaies; becauſe no man now doth caſt out Diuels bodily, nor cure diſeaſes, yet was not that promiſe of our ſauiours vaine, which hee would not haue to be alwaies effectuall, but for the time wherein the Church was borne and grew vp. With whom accordeth alſo our vnnaturall Countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Thomas Stapleton.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t opera mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculoſa tunc neceſſaria e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ad fidem hominum ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis ingeneran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſic poſtea bona opera Praedicatorum neceſſaria ſunt ad fidei opera producenda. Prompt. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. dominic. <hi>2.</hi> aduentus.</note> 
               <hi>As</hi> (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th he) <hi>miracles were need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the times of our Sauiour, that faith might bee bred in mens hearts; ſo afterwards the good workes of Preachers are neceſſarie, to bring foorth the workes of faith.</hi> Which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth with the teſtimonies of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Gregorie,</hi> which ye haue already heard.</p>
            <p>Now then, if <hi>S. Auguſtine, Chryſoſtome, Gregorie, Bede, Iſidore,</hi> be ancient and authenticall Doctors; if <hi>Catharine, Stella, Roffenſis, Stapleton,</hi> be learned Writers, as I aſſure my ſelfe <hi>Chambers</hi> dareth not gainſay; then we haue from them an anſwer to his demand, and prooued out of them, which he ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">In his epiſt. dedic.</note> can neuer be done, not only that true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and wrought by the finger of almighty God, are ceaſed in the Church, and the time when, (namely, when the world was generally brought to the faith of Chriſt:) but further, that ſuch as in the cleere Sun-ſhine light of the Goſpell, yet require miracles ſtill, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe, doe tempt God in ſo doing, that they are infidels, without faith and beleefe, that they loue not Chriſt as they ought to doe, that they are falſe Chriſtians, and hunters after vaine glorie. All which conuince <hi>Chambers</hi> of much ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, both in the ancient Fathers, and his owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Writers; and argue much folly in him, to conceiue, not only of his Maieſtie (whoſe wiſdome and learning all that know, admire) but of any of vs, that we ſhould be ſo ſimple and credulous, as to beleeue thoſe miracles, which the moſt learned amongſt them reiect as fabulous and fooliſh, as hath beene ſhewed.</p>
            <p>It irketh me to follow the purſuit of this ignorant Prieſt, who from his blunt arguments commeth in the end to the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19429:38"/> vſuall Popiſh rhetorike of railing and reuiling, tearming vs <hi>Heretikes,</hi> and ſpending his ieſts vpon vs;<note n="k" place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>who therfore thinke miracles ſuperfluous, becauſe we can worke none, as the fox will eat no grapes, becauſe he cannot get them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But laying aſide all bitterneſſe and ſcurrill ieſting in matters ſo weighty and ſerious, and to ſpeake the words of truth and ſoberneſſe; we therefore thinke miracles ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous vnto vs, not becauſe we can worke none, which we acknowledge, and therefore we attempt none; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we profeſſe the ſame doctrine which our Sauiour and his Apoſtles, and ſuch Apoſtolike men as ſucceeded in the Primitiue Church, haue confirmed to our hands, by ſo many true ſignes, and diuine miracles, which all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to vs and our Church, who profeſſe the ſame faith which our Sauiour and his Apoſtles preached.</p>
            <p>As for the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as it is new and ſtrangely degenerating from the ancient Catholike faith, ſo it is no maruell if it bee confirmed by new miracles, which are of the ſame nature with their new faith; falſe, both the one and the other.</p>
            <p>And yet to ſtop the mouths of our inſolent aduerſaries, which are alwaies craking of their miracles; if with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle eie they will looke vpon our Church, they may in it, and amongſt vs, behold ſuch miracles as make greatly for Gods glory, our priuate comfort, and the true honor of our Church.</p>
            <p>For both the reſtoring of the puritie of religion, in theſe late times, from the droſſe and corruptions of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> was not without the extraordinary and powerful working of almighty God; and the preſeruation thereof vnto this day, mauger all the conſpiracies and forces of our enemies againſt our Princes and our people, are ſuch as euince ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, that <hi>it is the Lords doing, and it is wonderfull in our eies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, if they will obſerue the fruit and efficacie of Gods word ſincerely preached amongſt vs, they may from thence behold<note n="l" place="margin">De verbis domini ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Matth. ſerm. <hi>18.</hi> See Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>6.</hi> in c. <hi>2.1</hi> ad Cor. <hi>And</hi> Greg hom. <hi>39.</hi> in Euangel. <hi>And</hi> Bernard. ſer. <hi>1.</hi> in aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione Domini. <hi>And</hi> Raban. in Pſal. <hi>9.</hi> Maius fuit Paulum paerſecutorem conuertere, quam Lazaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de monumento ſuſcitare, ib. Quae miracula tanto maiora <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unt, quanto per haec non corpora, ſed animae ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>maiores ſanitates,</hi> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19429:38"/> thoſe greater cures and greater wonders wrought amongſt vs in our Church, euen thoſe cures and wonders for which our Sauiour and his Apoſtles did vouchſafe to worke <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores illas,</hi> thoſe leſſer cures vpon mens bodies.</p>
            <p>For although now adaies <hi>coeca caro non aperit oculos mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculo Domini, the blinde man is not reſtored to his ſight by our Lords miracles;</hi> yet <hi>cor coecum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oculos ſermone Domini, the blinde heart of man openeth the eies of his vnderstanding, by the efficacie of his word preached amongst vs.</hi> The carcaſe that lieth dead in the graue, is not raiſed vp; but the ſoule that lieth dead, euen in the liuing body, by reaſon of ſinnes and treſpaſſes, is quickned amongſt vs, by the preaching of the Goſpell: the eares which were deafe before, and ſtopped at the crying of the poore; the hands which were faſt bound and ſhut from their releefe, are open to heare their groanes and requeſts, and looſed liberally for their comfort.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe your owne eies and eares this very day, heere at home amongſt your ſelues, which may heare and ſee the multitudes of Chriſt his poore and diſtreſſed mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; moſt charitably and carefully releeued in your<note n="m" place="margin">See the number of theſe poore, affixed to the Pſalme of thankſgiuing, ſung by the children of the Hoſpitall, vpon Munday in Eaſter weeke. 1609.</note> Hoſpitals, to the great glory of God, the comfort of the poore and afflicted, and the eternall memorie of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy founders and benefactors of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe abroad the planting intended, or rather alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy happily begun of our Engliſh Colonie in <hi>Virginia,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the charitie of our late Souereigne of all bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and of his moſt excellent Maieſty now reigning, aſſiſted with the godly indeuours of many chiefe and of principall note in this noble Citie, hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, to their great coſts, labours, and perils, for the gaining and winning to Chriſt his fold, and the reducing vnto a ciuill ſocietie (as hope may iuſtly conceiue) of ſo many thouſands of thoſe ſillie, brutiſh, and ignorant ſoules, now faſt bound with the chaines of error and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, vnder the bondage and ſlauery of the Diuell.</p>
            <p>Which being the principall ſcope of this buſineſſe, wee
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19429:39"/> may with Gods bleſſing aſſuredly expect the fruits which vſually accompany ſuch godly enterpriſes; as are the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Maieſtie, whoſe name ſhall by this meanes be glorious vnto the ends of the world, the enlarging and further ſtrengthning of his Realmes and Dominions, the eaſing of this Land, which euen groaneth vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and numbers of her i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bitants, the plentifull enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſelues and our Country with ſuch commodities as ſhe now laboureth with the penury of them: all which, and many other of this ſort, I wittingly paſſe-ouer, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene at ſundry times and places, by diuers of mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> abilitie and leiſure, commended to your godly conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: nothing remaining to be ſaid by mee in this kinde, but that with all thankfulneſſe we acknowledge, and with moſt hearty praiers wee commend to almighty God the happy preſeruation and continuance amongſt vs, of that noble inſtrument of his glory, our moſt gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lord <hi>King Iames,</hi> by whom he effecteth ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully his miraculous workes now adaies in our Church, to the wonder and aſtoniſhment of the world, not wilfully malignant.</p>
            <p>Thus if need were, we could ſpeake, and that without vanitie, of the true miracles of our Church: as for thoſe falſe &amp; fabulous ſorts which I haue touched, I leaue them to thoſe <hi>Mirabiliarij,</hi> as<note n="n" place="margin">Tractat. <hi>13.</hi> in Euangel. Johannis.</note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> calleth them, our Popiſh miracle-mongers, by which they are deſcried to be the very limmes of Antichriſt, and naturall brethren of theſe old Heretikes, the<note n="o" place="margin">Aug. de haereſ. c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Seuerians,</hi> and the<note n="p" place="margin">Id. de vnitat. Eccleſ. c. <hi>16.</hi> &amp; tractat. <hi>13,</hi> in Johan.</note> 
               <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and therefore thoſe <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> of which our Sauiour forewarned vs, when he ſaid, <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth inſtance which I propoſed as a note to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the true and falſe Prophets, is their life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation; which anſwering to true faith and doctrine, is a note of the true Prophet, it being ſincere and holy, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe if corrupt, a ſigne of the falſe. For<note n="q" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ex varijs in Mat. locis, hom. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Indicium me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis operata hominis, a mans work is the manifeſtation of his heart and minde,</hi> and therefore<note n="r" place="margin">Qui ouium indumento co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecti, quod profitentur, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famant, qui aliud docent, quam faciunt, &amp;c, ib.</note> 
               <hi>though hee bee cloathed with
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19429:39"/> the Sheepes weede, if he teach one thing and doe another, if hee be a ſhame and obloquie to his profeſſion, he is a falſe Prophet,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ibid.</note> as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> rightly obſerueth from the words of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>ye ſhall know them by their fruites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heere then if I ſhould goe about to rip vp the liues of the Romiſh Praelates: as there would be no end of it, ſo the ſauour therof would be moſt vnpleaſant and offenſiue to your chaſt ſenſes; which I could make euident, not as they do from the ſlanderous reports of <hi>Bolſeck, Coclaeus, Staphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> and ſuch companions, againſt our reuerend Paſtors, <hi>Luther, Caluin, Beza,</hi> to whome they were profeſſed ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: but out of their own writers, and ſome of them ſo neere, as that they were eye-witneſſes of the things which they report.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaid long ſince of <hi>Rome</hi> heatheniſh,<note n="t" place="margin">Quò cuncta vndiqueatrocia ac pude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flu unt celebra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Annal. l. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That all ſhameleſſe and heinous enormities ran into it,</hi> as into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſewer, which <hi>Theodoricus</hi> of<note n="u" place="margin">Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nilo porte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta paris, nutris crocodilos, &amp;c. de ſciſma l. <hi>3.6 41.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Niem</hi> one attending ſometime on the Pope, maketh good vpon <hi>Rome popiſh</hi> applying certaine verſes vnto it, wherein it is compared with <hi>Nilus</hi> which bred monſters, and nouriſhed Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles. And there Saint <hi>Bridget</hi> affirmed, <hi>that ſhe heard the bleſſed Virgin ſaying to her Sonne, that</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe ferace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondiſſe vero christu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſt, ſed zizaniae cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. teſt verit. to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>800.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rome was a fruitful field, to whome Chriſt ſhould anſwer, it was ſo indeede, but the fruitfulneſſe thereof conſiſted in tares.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſtol.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>Petrarch calleth it the mother of al Idolatrie, the refuge and Sanctuarie of all errors.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Miniſtri chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti ſunt, et ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto. ſer. <hi>33.</hi> in Cantica.</note> 
               <hi>Bernards</hi> complaints are not ſo many, as iuſt; he ſaith of the whole Clergie, <hi>that in name they are the Miniſters of Chriſt, but in very deede the Seruants of Antichriſt, whoſe ſins were growne to that height,</hi> as<note n="a" place="margin">Vitia noſtra eo creuere, vt vix apud deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſericordiae locum nobis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquerînt, in vita Marcel. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi> one of the Popes Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries reporteth, <hi>that they ſcarcely left any roome with God for his mercie.</hi> Now all theſe, and many of this ſort put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſay no more then what Pope<note n="b" place="margin">Nos ſcimus quod in hac ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ſede, ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis aliquot mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta fuerunt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominabilia <hi>&amp;c</hi> Nec miru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quod infirmitas a capite in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra, a Papis in minores prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos deriuarit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> paralipome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad Chro. Abatis vſperg.</note> 
               <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſixt gaue his Legate in charge to confeſſe before the States of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> at a meeting of theirs, <hi>that Rome had for many yeares together offended, and that many waies, and that all</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Plurimis. nunc annis grauiter mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> modis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum eſſe Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, et inde a Pontificio cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine malu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hoc at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> luem ad inferiores omnes eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Praeſectus defluxiſſe. Slei dan Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and infection, flowed from the Pope, as from the head vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the inferior and lower Praelates;</hi> according with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19429:40"/> 
               <hi>Ieremy,</hi> c. 23. verſ. 15. <hi>From the Prophets of Ieruſalem, is wickedneſſe gone foorth into all the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Habetis confitentem reum,</hi> ye heare the Pope anſwer guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the crimes obiected, what neede then haue wee of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more witneſſes? If<note n="d" place="margin">Decima no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt ſanctitas vitae Auctorum ſiue primorum patrum noſtra religionis. De notis Eccleſ. li. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ſanctitie of life, eſpecially of chiefe Paſtors, be a note of the church, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, then a <hi>contrario,</hi> the wicked and abhominable life of our Romiſh Praelates, argue ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly that they are the falſe Prophets of which our Sauiour gaue vs this watch-word, <hi>beware of falſe Prophets.</hi> Whereby it appeareth what may bee infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon that Antecedent, which<note n="e" place="margin">In his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his Detection of Maſter <hi>Iewels</hi> errors &amp; lies.</note> 
               <hi>Thomas Harding</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe maketh and acknowledgeth. <hi>What if Popes haue ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red great Princes and Monarkes to kiſſe their feete, to hold their Stirrops, to leade their Horſes by the Bridle? What if a Pope ſhewed himſelfe cruel and without pittie, in ſuffering</hi> Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Dandalus <hi>the Venetians Ambaſſador to lie vnder his table like a Dog, whiles he was at dinner? What if Pope Alexander vſed Fredericke the Emperor more proudly, then became a man of his calling? What if the Popes at certaine times cared not, or, for the wretchedneſſe of Mans ill inclination could not, or for greate conſiderations would not vtterly purge the Citie of Rome, of Curteſans and Brodel-houſes? What if the life of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny Prieſts, Biſhops, Cardinalls yea of ſome Popes alſo, hath iuſtly deſerued to bee reprooued? muſt this now bee made a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; ſome of their liues were ſinfull, ergo their Doctrine was falſe? Not ſo M. Harding, wee conclude not ſo, but wee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer out of</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Hom. <hi>11.</hi> ex variis in Mat. locis.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtom and</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">De notis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> ca. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine: the liues of many your Popes and chief praelats, were moſte ſinful, flagitious and heinos: therfore they were no ſound members of the true Church; but ſuch falſe Prophets, as beeing cloathed with Sheepe ſkins, are not-withſtanding inwardly no better then rauening Wolues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How then commeth it to paſſe (belooued in the Lord) that this famous and ancient City of London, the Mother Citie of the Kingdome, the beautie and glorie of the land, is become a cage of theſe vncleane and filthie Birds, and a Den for ſuch rauening wolues, as thirſt after nothing more then your blood, and that not of the bodie alone,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19429:40"/> but much more of your ſoules?<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> haue yee beene deliuered from the bondage and darkenes of Aegipt, into the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous libertie of the Sonnes of God, and ſun-ſhine light of the Goſpell, to returne againe in your hearts, into bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and darkenes, more then Aegyptiacal? Shal I demand with the Apoſtle, <hi>Who hath bewitched you that yee ſhould not obey the truth?</hi> Are they theſe popiſh Syrens, with their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring ſongs of hope, and expectation of a golden day, ſo long expected, and ſo hopefullie conceiued in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining age of that moſt renowned Q. Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our late Soueraigne? But the tune of that Song is altered, (God haue the glorie for it) &amp; they lament anotherwhile (and ſo may they euer) with <hi>O ſpes fallaces,</hi> O our deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hopes, our vaine dreames, our idle imaginations:<note n="h" place="margin">D. Biſhop in his Epiſt. to the King.</note> the ſtate is now ſetled (they ſay) and ſo let it be, O Lord, euen for euer and euer) and a continuall poſteritie is like to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of one nature and condition, <hi>Amen Lord Ieſu.</hi> Is it the ſplendor of their miracles, which ſo long haue dazeled the eies of the World? but theſe are conuinced to be falſe and fabulous; or no better, then the workings of Satan, and illuſions of Antichriſt. Is it the ſinceritie of their doct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rine? but that is no better then the Beggars cloake, patched together of olde haereſies, long ſince condemned by the Catholike Church, as in part hath been ſhewed, and may as eaſily be proued in the reſt.<note n="i" place="margin">See Faxa ſacrae paniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiariae.</note> They rob God of his honor, and giue it to ſtockes and ſtones: they take Chriſt his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice from him, and ioyne Saints with him in his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Gods ſacred word is but a bable with them; and of no worth, in regard of their traditions, and vnwritten verities: their religion is the high way to Atheiſme, and al impiety; there beeing no ſinne ſo heinous, ſo enormous which they diſpenſe not with by their indulgencies: and pardon by their abſolutions, inceſt, rapes, murders, vowes, periuries, all veniall, ſo money be not wanting.</p>
            <p>Their profeſſion is knowne to be the dethroning and murthering of princes: and for their practiſe it is the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ouerthrow of ciuil ſtates, and ſocieties, by ſwearing and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19429:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> forſwearing, by Aequiuocating and diſſembling, taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away all truth and ſincere dealing from amongſt men. As for their life and maners; no puddle is more impure then this ſinck:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.26.28. <hi>et</hi> v. 21.</note> and that by the iuſt iudgement of Almightie God, <hi>God giuing them vp to vile affections, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reprobate minde becauſe that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankeful,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the Gentiles, and is as truely verified in the Romaniſts.</p>
            <p>So that if any man heere preſent, will ſtill bee miſled &amp; ſeduced by the falſe Prophets, notwithſtanding the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that hath beene giuen, I muſt pronounce of him, (though with much greefe of heart) that hee is guiltie of his owne blood,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 33.4.</note> his blood bee vppon his owne head; for my part, I ſay, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is in the Prophet, for the integritie of my conſcience, &amp; diſcharge of this duetie, <hi>liberaui animam meam,</hi> I haue deliuered my owne ſoule, now look ye to it.</p>
            <p>But for you (belooued in the Lord, of whome we haue perſwaded our ſelues better things, &amp; ſuch as accompanie ſaluation) ſtand faſt, I beſeech you, in the bowels of Chriſt, in the Doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles, which yee haue receiued, grounded vpon Chriſt the Corner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and ſealed vnto you with his blood, and with the blood of his holy Martyrs in all ages; and beware of falſe Prophets, beware of theſe Sheep-skin'd wolues: trie their ſpirits, examine their faith, looke into their manners: by theſe fruits you may know them; and knowing them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid their ſteps which leade to hel and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which that yee may bee able to doe, that God of mercies, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all goodnes, which commanded the light to ſhine out of darkenes, illighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eyes of your vnderſtandings, confirme you with his grace, and guide you with his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit amidſt the ſtormes of theſe laſt &amp; perilous times, that ſo in the end yee may ariue at the hauen of all bliſſe and happineſſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19429:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
